<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MS9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Medicine and Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2049-0801</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40109609</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11918640</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AMSU-D-24-00533</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MS9.0000000000002778</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00028</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Revolutionizing electrocardiography: the role of artificial intelligence in modern cardiac diagnostics</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qayyum</surname><given-names>Sardar N.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>dr.sardarnoman@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iftikhar</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>dr.sardarnoman@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rehan</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>rehanabbaxi123@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aziz Khan</surname><given-names>Gulmeena</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>gulmeenaazizkhan@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Maleeka</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>maleekak19@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Naeem</surname><given-names>Risha</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>Risha.naeem.1020@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>Rafay S.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>Rafayansari1@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>Irfan</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>Uirfan605@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Noori</surname><given-names>Samim</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>sameemnoori@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Bacha Khan Medical College, Mardan, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Khyber Medical College, Peshawar, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Al-Nafees Medical College and Hospital, Islamabad, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Ameer-ud-din Medical College, University of Health Sciences, Lahore, Lahore, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Ziauddin Medical University, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Nangarhar University Faculty of Medicine, Nangarhar, Afghanistan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Faculty of Medicine, Nangarhar University, Jalalabad, Nangarhar, Afghanistan. E-mail: <email>sameemnoori@gmail.com</email> (S. Noori).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>87</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0</ext-link> (CCBY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ms9-87-161.pdf"/><abstract><p>Electrocardiography (ECG) remains a cornerstone of non-invasive cardiac diagnostics, yet manual interpretation poses challenges due to its complexity and time consumption. The integration of Artificial Intelligence (AI), particularly through Deep Learning (DL) models, has revolutionized ECG analysis by enabling automated, high-precision diagnostics. This review highlights the recent advancements in AI-driven ECG applications, focusing on arrhythmia detection, abnormal beat classification, and the prediction of structural heart diseases. AI algorithms, especially convolutional neural networks (CNNs), have demonstrated superior accuracy compared to human experts in several studies, achieving precise classification of ECG patterns across multiple diagnostic categories. Despite the promise, real-world implementation faces challenges, including model interpretability, data privacy concerns, and the need for diversified training datasets. Addressing these challenges through ongoing research will be crucial to fully realize AI&#x02019;s potential in enhancing clinical workflows and personalizing cardiac care. AI-driven ECG systems are poised to significantly advance the accuracy, efficiency, and scalability of cardiac diagnostics.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>electrocardiogram</kwd><kwd>artificial intelligence</kwd><kwd>machine learning</kwd><kwd>deep learning</kwd><kwd>ECG databases</kwd><kwd>precision cardiology</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Artificial Intelligence (AI) makes machines capable of simulating intelligence and endows them with human-like capabilities such as understanding, reasoning, decision-making, problem-solving and performing complex tasks with varying degrees of autonomy<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup>. In healthcare, AI-powered technologies have been used for analysis and interpretation of various medical images such as X-rays, CT-scan for diagnosis and risk predictions. Various AI algorithms have been developed and improved over time for ECG analysis as well<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Machine learning (ML), a subtype of AI, focuses on the development of algorithms and statistical techniques that enable computer systems to learn from the datasets, identify patterns and predict outcomes based on the input data. ML approaches include supervised learning, unsupervised learning, reinforcement learning and deep learning (DL)<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup>. In supervised learning, algorithms are trained on labeled datasets to predict outcomes on new, unseen data while in unsupervised learning, algorithm learns patterns in datasets to predict outcomes in new data without human supervision. Reinforcement learning makes computer systems to learn to make decisions and solve problems by themselves based on a reward and penalty systems as in robotics. Deep learning (DL) is a subset of ML, which uses neural networks to learn from large datasets and extract hidden patterns. These multilayered neural networks consist of interconnected nodes organized in layers that mimic human brain in structure and function. DL requires large datasets to train effectively and can also learn automatically from unstructured data unlike ML which often requires manual feature extraction and selection. DL networks, such as CNNs (convolutional neural networks), has feature extraction layers also known as convolutional filters which automatically extracts features from the data and model layers to analyze the extracted features<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup>. Thus, DL models learn features relevant to the task directly from the data avoiding human bias and the need for manual feature engineering<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup>. Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> summarizes the relationship of AI, ML, and DL.
<fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>The relationship between AI, ML, and DL.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-161-g001" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>AI has been adopted to analyze routine 12-lead ECGs after being widely used in computer-vision, image processing and speech recognition. AI applications in ECG analysis include simple rule-based models to state-of-the art DL models that can mimic human-like interpretation. The DL models such as CNN can learn from temporal information to detect voltage variations or spatial information to locate myocardial infarction<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup>. CNNs are the most widely used models in AI-ECG systems for tasks like arrhythmia detection, abnormal beat classification, and structural heart disease prediction. CNNs excel at learning spatial and temporal patterns in ECG signals, which makes them ideal for analyzing ECG data with time-series characteristics. CNNs involve operations such as &#x0201c;convolutions&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;pooling,&#x0201d; which can become computationally expensive, especially when applied to long ECG recordings with multiple leads. The computational complexity increases significantly as the number of filters or inputs size grows, especially when applied to 12-lead ECGs<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Artificial intelligence (AI) has emerged as a transformative force across various medical specialties, revolutionizing both clinical support and data interpretation. In radiology, AI is being harnessed to enhance diagnostic precision, with continuous learning algorithms enabling faster and more accurate detection of abnormalities in imaging studies such as CT scans and MRIs<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup>. In oncology, AI-driven models are being utilized from early cancer detection to personalized treatment planning, improving patient outcomes through tailored therapies. Similarly, in cardiology, AI is being integrated into echocardiogram analysis, enabling automated detection of heart abnormalities and predictive analytics for future cardiovascular events. Dentistry is also benefiting from AI, particularly in dental implant planning, where machine learning algorithms optimize treatment strategies based on patient-specific data. Moreover, in specialties such as pathology, AI is assisting in the analysis of tissue samples, improving diagnostic accuracy and reducing human error.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup></p><p>In this review, we aim to address the following research question: How can AI, particularly deep learning models, be utilized to enhance the accuracy, efficiency, and diagnostic capabilities of electrocardiogram (ECG) analysis, with a specific focus on arrhythmia detection, structural cardiac abnormalities, and long-term cardiac monitoring? Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the working of AI algorithms in ECG analysis termed &#x0201c;AI-ECG systems.&#x0201d;
<fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The functioning of AI-ECG systems.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-161-g002" position="float"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec><title>Methodology</title><p>We searched the last 5&#x000a0;years literature on databases such as PubMed, Scopus, Google scholar using search terms such as &#x0201c;Artificial Intelligence,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Deep learning,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN),&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Electrocardiogram,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;ECG,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Arrhythmia Detection,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Abnormal Beats,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Atrial Fibrillation,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Structural Heart diseases.&#x0201d; We initially screened 70 studies published in peer-reviewed journals. We included papers published within last 5&#x000a0;years that focused on the applications of AI, ML, and DL in the analysis and interpretation of ECG. Studies not related to AI or ECG, or published before 2018, non-peer-reviewed articles, opinions, pieces, or commentaries were excluded. Studies not available in English were also excluded. We included a total of 51 studies focusing on the applications of AI, ML, and DL on ECG analysis and interpretation with special focus on arrhythmia detection, structural cardiac abnormalities, and long-term cardiac monitoring.</p></sec><sec><title>A review of applications of AI in ECG analysis</title><sec><title>Technical specifications of major ECG datasets</title><p>The ECG datasets have a spatial axis which refers to voltage recordings of different leads measuring the heart&#x02019;s electrical activity from different angles and a temporal axis which reflects changes in voltage over time. The technical specifications of major ECG datasets have been given in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.
<table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Technical specifications of various important ECG databases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content description</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Channels</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annotations</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIH-BIH Data</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 half-hour excerpts of 2-channel ambulatory ECG recordings from 47 subjects</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each recording is 30&#x000a0;minutes long</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beat annotations including types and location of arrhythmias</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PhysioNet Computing in Cardiology (CinC) Challenge dataset</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual challenge datasets with varying content</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Varies from 1 to 12 leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#x000a0;s to several minutes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific to each year&#x02019;s challenge; often include arrhythmia types, signal quality indicators, etc.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTB Diagnostic ECG Database</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">549 records from 290 subjects, including healthy controls and patients with various conditions</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 leads including 12 leads&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;3 Frank leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each recording is approx. 2&#x000a0;min long</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnoses and signal quality indicators</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">St. Petersburg INCART Database</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 annotated recordings 32 Holter monitor files of 32 subjects</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each recording is 30&#x000a0;minutes long</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beat annotations, rhythm changes, and arrhythmias</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chapman Shaoxing and Ningbo Hospital database</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Over 45&#x000a0;000 ECG recordings</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each recording is 10&#x000a0;s long</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detailed annotations include rhythm types, noise levels, and clinical findings</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lobachevsky University Electrocardiography Database</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contains 200 ECG recordings</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each recording is 10&#x000a0;s long</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beat annotation, rhythm changes, and clinical annotations</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Georgia 12-lead ECG challenge Database</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Over 10&#x000a0;000 12-lead ECGs used in PhysioNet 2020</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each recording is 10&#x000a0;s to 2&#x000a0;min long</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beat annotation, rhythm classification, and clinical diagnoses</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long-term ST database</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 long-term ECG recordings of 80 subjects</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 or more leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each recording is 21 to 24&#x000a0;h long</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST segment annotations and ischemic events</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European ST-T database</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 annotated ECG recordings from 79 subjects</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each recording is 2&#x000a0;h long</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annotations of ST-T segment changes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSE Database</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard ECG database for validation of AI algorithms</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each recording is 10&#x000a0;s long</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical annotations and diagnostic markers</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QT Database</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 ECG recordings annotated with QT intervals</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each recording is 15&#x000a0;min long</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QT interval annotations and arrhythmia markers</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mayo clinic database</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Over 10 million ECG recordings</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 leads</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each recording is 10&#x000a0;s long</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beat annotation, rhythm classification, clinical diagnoses, etc.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec><title>AI for abnormal beat detection</title><p>Abnormal Heartbeats can either be ectopic beats and arrhythmias when they form a specific pattern. Although ectopic beats have less clinical relevance for healthy patients but in CVD patients may have more significance and can be indicative of higher arrhythmia risks<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup>. Classification AI models make use of supervised data mining technique wherein a model is trained on labeled ECG datasets in which input data is paired with correct output. During the training phase, the model learns to associate input features with specific categories and distinguish between normal and abnormal beats and rhythms. This supervised approach ensures that the AI systems can accurately categorize new, unseen ECG data, thereby enhancing diagnostic precision and potentially identifying cardiac abnormalities with greater reliability<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup>. DL algorithms are well-suited for complex datasets and their performance also improves with exposure to larger datasets. DL models achieved higher performance metrics than other AI techniques in several studies. A DL approach, 1D-CNN, has been developed in a study by Malik <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> to detect ectopic beats such as ventricular and supra-ventricular beats. The model achieved an accuracy of 98% and 99.04% for supra-ventricular and ventricular ectopic beats respectively. In another study, Li <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> developed GRNN (general regression neural network) for beat classification and the model achieved an accuracy of up to 95%. A CNN model<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> was developed which could classify heartbeats into five classes, i.e., supraventricular ectopic, ventricular ectopic, non-ectopic, fusion and unknown beats. The model achieved an accuracy of above 90%. Noises in datasets may lead to misinterpretation and misdiagnosis thus the accuracy of AI model declined to 89% in noisy ECGs. Noises in ECG data can arise from various sources, such as muscle activity, baseline wander, motion artifacts, power-line interference, and electrode displacement. CNN models will perform well with minor noise, but their performance degrades as noise increases because CNNs rely heavily on spatial feature extraction, and noise in the spatial domain can corrupt features used for classification such as QRS complex, P wave, and T wave. 1D-CNNs can also be affected by noise, but they may show better resilience due to their focus on temporal data. However, when the noise is persistent across time-series data, the model may struggle to distinguish between signal and noise. GRNNs tends to be highly sensitive to noisy data because they are non-parametric models that use entire training set for predictions, any noise in the dataset can propagate into model&#x02019;s predictions.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup></p><p>Another study developed a semi-supervised model by using DL approach Gaussian-Bernoulli deep belief network (GB-DBN) along with an SVM classifier<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup>. The model was trained, tested and validated across two MIT-BIH databases for the classification of SVEB and VEB. DBN and SVM are hybrid models useful when labeled data is scarce, but these models tend to be computationally heavy during training especially when applied to large-scale ECG datasets, but are less computationally intensive than CNN-based models<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup>. The proposed model<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup> works in three phases. In the first phase, the GB-DBN learns the feature representation in the datasets followed by SVM classifier&#x02019;s learning the classification. The last phase is characterized by an active learning phase where it interacts with an expert for ambiguous beats classification. Initially, the model achieved 91.3% sensitivity, 98.52% specificity, and 98.1% overall accuracy for VEB which improved to 98.47% sensitivity, 99.5% specificity, and 99.42% accuracy after multiple queries with experts. Similarly, the model achieved an initial sensitivity of 38.8%, 99.2% specificity, and 97.5% accuracy for SVEB which improved to 94.3% sensitivity, 99.71% specificity, and 99.6% overall accuracy. In another study, a rule-based system was developed to detect ischemic and arrhythmic heartbeats<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup>. The rule-based model achieved 91% sensitivity and 92% specificity for an ischemic beat while 96% sensitivity and 99% specificity for all other categories indicating the proposed model could be applied to clinical settings for ECG analysis. In the above studies, AI has demonstrated the feasibility of fast, accurate and personalized beat classification. These models are useful for patient&#x02019;s ECG data requiring long-term cardiac monitoring for abnormal beat detection with higher accuracy.</p></sec><sec><title>AI for arrhythmia detection</title><p>AI algorithms focused on the analysis of the broader pattern of irregular heart activity over time have been developed for the detection and classification of arrhythmias such as atrial fibrillation (AFib), bradycardia, tachycardia, and ventricular fibrillation, with higher or comparable accuracy than cardiologists<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>AFib detection</title><p>AFib is the most common type of arrhythmias and is mostly asymptomatic until late complications such as thrombosis, stroke, and heart failure. Attia <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup> developed a CNN model to analyze standard 12 ECGs during normal rhythm and identify patients with history of AFib. The model was trained with over 650&#x000a0;000 ECGs from the Mayo Clinic Database and tested on dataset of over 35&#x000a0;000 patients. Initially the model achieved an AUC of 0.87, 79% sensitivity, 80% specificity and 79% accuracy. However, as the performance of DL models improve with time, so after 1&#x000a0;month the performance of the DL model increased. It achieved an AUC of 0.90 with sensitivity of 82%, specificity and accuracy of 83%. AI offers a rapid, inexpensive way to detect patients with undetected AFib using standard ECGs during normal sinus rhythm unlike to conventional techniques that involve long-term cardiac monitoring. In another study, Raghunath <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup> developed a deep neural network to predict new-onset of AFib within 1 year. The algorithm was trained on a larger dataset of over 1.6 million standard ECGs obtained from 253,387 patients. The training dataset included 99,371 patients with previous AFib episodes. The model was evaluated on a test set of 168,914 patients, in which 14,207 AFib episodes had occurred and it achieved an AUC of 0.88. Thus, the application of DL includes not only detection of AFib but also identification of patients at greater risk of recurrence.</p></sec><sec><title>Ventricular arrhythmia (VA) detection</title><p>Ventricular arrhythmias such as ventricular tachycardia (VT) and premature ventricular complexes (PVC) result into the deterioration of LV ejection fraction. Rapid detection and application of defibrillators are crucial for treating life-threatening arrhythmias<sup>[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup>. Sabut <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup> trained, tested and validated a DNN model on two public-domain ECG databases. The model achieved better performance than any standard ML-based classifier, i.e., an accuracy of 99.2% with sensitivity of 98.8% and specificity of 99.3%. Another study applied the CNN model to locate the source of VA from standard 12 ECGs achieving an AUC of 0.963 for binary classification as right or left VA and an AUC of 0.998 for detecting VA originating from LV summit. The proposed DL algorithms could not only detect VTA accurately but also locate the VTA source improving the efficiency of cardiac diagnosis and guiding catheter ablation.</p></sec><sec><title>AI as a unified solution for multiclass arrhythmia classification</title><p>An ensemble model, STA-CRNN, developed by Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup> classified standard ECGs into normal heart rhythms and 8 classes of arrhythmias including AFib, 1-AVB, LBBB, RBBB, PAC, PVC, ST-segment depression and ST-segment elevation. The model&#x02019;s architecture was based on CNN&#x02019;s local feature extraction and RNN&#x02019;s global feature extraction abilities and the spatiotemporal attention module compensates for the noise in the dataset. The classification model was trained on the CPSC database and achieved an average F1 score of 0.835. Several of the AI classification models can classify multi-lead ECGs into 20 or more diagnostic classes. Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> developed an ensemble model by combining a rule-based system and two SE_ResNet (an ANN) models to classify 27 cardiac abnormalities including AFib, AFL, bradycardia, bundle branch blocks, PVC, prolonged QT interval, prolonged PR interval, sinus arrhythmias, T-wave abnormalities, etc. The initial framework of SE_ResNet is based on CNN architecture. The sign loss function is used in addition to dealing with noise in data and improving the generalizability. It was trained and tested on 6 different PhysioNet datasets and ranked 3rd in the PhysioNet/Computing in Cardiology Challenge 2020. Xu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> developed a more robust DL model to classify ECGs into 30 cardiac abnormalities The model was trained, validated and trained on PhysioNet dataset and achieved higher accuracy AUC (&#x0003e; 0.90) for sinus bradycardia, sinus tachycardia, AFL, LBBB, RBBB, IAVB, LAD, LAnFB, NSR, etc., using standard 12-Lead ECGs and 2-Lead ECGs. These models are recommended for use in clinical settings to detect multiple classes of arrhythmias.</p></sec><sec><title>AI as high precision tool for multiclass arrhythmia classification</title><p>Several AI models demonstrated 99% or more accuracy in beat and arrhythmia classification. Haseena <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup> developed an ensemble model by combining fuzzy expert rule-based system with deep neural networks for arrhythmia classification. The figure demonstrates the step-by-step implementation of the proposed AI model. The extracted features included ST segment duration, QT interval, PR interval, RR interval, R amplitude and QRS width. The model achieved an accuracy of 97% to 99.5% in classifying normal rhythms, LBBB, RBBB, PVC, APB, PB, VFW, and VEB. Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> highlights the step-by-step functioning of the ensemble model.
<fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>The working of proposed ensemble model.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-161-g003" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>In another study, an ensemble AI model<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> was developed by combining CNN and LSTM techniques to classify variable length ECGs into normal heart rhythms, PVC, LBBB, APB and RBBB. LSTM models are used for learning temporal dependencies in sequential data like ECG signals, and are employed usually for tasks like arrhythmia detection and long-term cardiac monitoring to detect abnormal patterns overtime. Due to additional parameters, LSTM models are computationally expensive as compared to other deep networks<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup>. The proposed model<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> was trained and tested on PhysioNet public domain dataset and achieved 98.1% accuracy along with 97.5% sensitivity and 98.7% specificity.</p></sec><sec><title>AI outperforms expert cardiologists</title><p>AI has outperformed expert cardiologists in arrhythmia classification. In a study, Hannun <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup> developed a DNN model to classify standard ECGs into 12 arrhythmic classes including AFib, AFL, AVB, SVT, VT, Wenckebach, trigeminy, bigeminy, ectopic atrial rhythm, idioventricular rhythm, junctional rhythm, etc. The algorithm achieved an average F1 score of 0.837, more than expert cardiologists&#x02019; 0.780 with an AUC of 0.977, sensitivity and specificity of&#x000a0;&#x0003e;90%. In another study, LSTM model<sup>[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> was developed to classify the above given 12 arrhythmia classes using standard 12-Lead ECGs. The DL technique outperformed interns, emergency physicians and cardiologists. Internists achieved an overall accuracy of 55%, emergency physicians 73%, cardiologists 83%, and LSTM model 90%.</p><p>The state-of-the art diagnostic AI algorithms have outworked physicians in detection of conduction abnormalities, structural abnormalities and MI in addition to arrhythmia detection. Hughes <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</sup> developed a CNN-based models on University of California, San Francisco dataset for the classification of 38 cardiac abnormalities. These abnormalities include PVC, PAC, AVB, LBBB, RBBB, QT prolongation, Wolff-Parkinson-White, ventricular hypertrophy, atrial enlargement, MI, etc. The model was validated against cardiologists&#x02019; diagnosis and consensus committee diagnosis comprising of electrophysiologists. The CNN model achieved an AUC of 0.91 and had comparable average F1 scores and higher sensitivity than cardiologists. Compared to another automated ECG system, MUSE, the current framework had higher F1 scores for all classes except SVT.</p></sec><sec><title>AI for long-term cardiac monitoring</title><p>Holter monitors or insertable cardiac monitors (ICM) are used to monitor cardiac electrical activity for a longer time to reach quality diagnoses in certain diseases. It leads to the accumulation of large ECG data<sup>[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</sup>. A DNN based model was developed<sup>[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</sup> on 1000 Holter recordings to detect the presence or absence of 5 cardiac abnormalities, i.e., VT, AFib, AFL, AT, AVB, and PVC. The algorithm was compared to traditional diagnostic platforms. Although no significant differences in sensitivity, accuracy and specificity were found except for AFib and VT but AI-analysis was 25% faster than conventional system which included electrophysiologists analysis of Holter recordings. The model demonstrated the feasibility of rapid, accurate analysis of Holter recordings with sensitivity and specificity ranging from 0.93 to 1 and 0.98 to 1, respectively.</p><p>ICM is employed to detect various types of arrhythmias, risks of cardiac adverse events, personalized treatment and real-time monitoring of electrical activity of heart. Quartier <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</sup> employed AI algorithms for the analysis of ICM data collected over 23&#x000a0;months from 20 patients for arrhythmia detection. The AI model achieved 95.4% accuracy with 97.19% sensitivity, and 94.52% specificity for various classes of arrhythmias. It reduced the false positive arrhythmia by 98% overall. Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> summarizes the AI&#x02019;s role in ICM.
<fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Applications of AI in ICM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-161-g004" position="float"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec><title>AI-ECG for LVH</title><p>LVH is the consequence of myocardial hypertrophy. Although echocardiography is the gold standard for diagnosis but it can also be detected through ECGs as with increased myocardium, the amplitude for QRS complex also increases and electrical activity takes longer to transverse through the whole myocardium leading to QRS widening along with ST segment deviation. On ECG, a typical pattern in LVH includes ST segment deviation in opposite to QRS complex and T wave inversion. Several ECG criteria such as Cornell and Sokolow-Lyon have been developed. Lui <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</sup> developed a DL-augmented back-propagation neural network (BPN) model to detect LVH. The model extracted 24 features from the dataset followed by segmentation of individual beats in each case. In the end the BPN was trained using the extracted features. The model achieved 96.1% accuracy, 95.8% precision, 96.6% sensitivity and 95.6% specificity and outperformed all other ECG-LVH diagnostic criteria and other ML techniques.</p></sec><sec><title>AI-ECG for asymptomatic ventricular dysfunction</title><p>ALVD is present in 3% to 6% of the individuals. AI can serve as a powerful tool for the detection of asymptomatic ventricular dysfunction. Attia <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</sup> developed a CNN-based diagnostic system to detect ALVD from standard 12 lead ECGs. The model was trained, tested and validated on the Mayo Clinic ECGs database and it achieved an accuracy of 85.7% along with a sensitivity 86.3%, specificity of 85.7%, and AUC 0.93. AI-positive for ALVD was found to be 4 times more at risk for symptomatic ventricular dysfunction.</p></sec><sec><title>AI-ECG for HF</title><p>HFrEF is caused mainly by systolic dysfunction. AI-ECG models are of diagnostic importance for detection of HF from single lead ECGs as well as multiple lead ECGs. J Cho <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</sup> developed a CNN model to detect HFrEF (reduced ejection fraction is defined as&#x000a0;&#x0003c;40%) from standard 12-Lead ECGs and single Lead ECGs as well. The model was trained, tested and validated on ECGs datasets from two hospitals. Upon internal and external validation of the model on standard 12-Lead ECGs, the model achieved an AUC of 0.913 and 0.961 respectively. With single-lead ECGs, the model achieved an AUC of 0.874 and 0.929 upon internal and external validation respectively demonstrating the diagnostic importance of single lead ECGs from the wearable devices for early screening of HF. Attia <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</sup> in a study developed a DL-algorithm to detect reduced ejection fraction from ECGs datasets obtained from Apple smartwatches with an AUC of 0.88. The study findings suggest that single lead ECGs from smartwatches obtained in non-clinical environment can be useful with AI integration.</p></sec><sec><title>AI-ECG for CA</title><p>Stiff heart syndrome is also termed as cardiac amyloidosis (CA). AI can detect CA with higher accuracy. A study by Grogan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</sup> demonstrated the potential of AI algorithms in CA screening from multiple Lead ECGs. The DNN model was trained, tested and validated on Mayo Clinic ECGs database. The 6-lead ECGs model achieved an AUC of 0.90 with precision of 0.85 for CA on single-lead ECGs, the model achieved an AUC of 0.86 with a precision of 0.78. This model could also predict CA progression 6&#x000a0;months earlier. In another study, an ML approach was utilized to detect multiple CVDs including CA, HTN, HCM, etc., with higher accuracy demonstrating the potential advantages of earlier screening.</p></sec><sec><title>AI-ECG for valvular diseases</title><p>Valvular stenosis has a longstanding asymptomatic period and poor prognosis. However, AI-ECG systems can help with early screening of valve stenosis and regurgitation. Kwon <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> developed DL models to detect aortic stenosis<sup>[<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</sup> and mitral regurgitation<sup>[<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</sup> with AUC of 0.816 to 0.884. Sensitivity maps reveal that DL algorithms analyze T waves from precordial leads to detect aortic stenosis while for mitral regurgitation analyzes both T-waves and P-waves in patients with mitral regurgitation.</p></sec><sec><title>AI-ECG for MI detection</title><p>The advancements in AI especially the development of DL algorithms have enabled the invention of automated diagnosis systems with performance comparable to or better than physicians. In a study, Makimoto <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</sup> developed a 6-layered CNN model to detect MI from multi-lead ECGs. The proposed framework was trained, and tested on the PTB diagnosis ECG database which contains ECGs from 290 patients. The model achieved higher sensitivity, accuracy and specificity with 12-Leads ECGs as compared to 9-Lead ECGs and 6-Lead ECGs. The framework was also tested with 10 physicians for the recognition of MI with 72 ECGs. The model achieved a higher F1 score (0.83) and accuracy (81%) as compared to physicians.</p></sec><sec><title>AI-ECG for risk prediction</title><p>AI-based ECG system has revolutionized the field of cardiology, particularly in the realm of risk prediction and early detection of cardiovascular events. These advance systems make use of various algorithms and data mining techniques to help identify patterns, and correlations, and trends essential for accurate risk prediction. These techniques make use of various algorithms and statistical models to analyze vast amounts of ECG data, electronic healthcare records, and other relevant medical information. The insights gained from this extensive analysis enable AI systems to refine their predictive models, improve diagnostic accuracy, and provide personalized recommendations for patient care. For instance, AI-ECG systems can reveal previously unnoticed relationships between specific ECG features and the likelihood of developing certain conditions.</p><p>One notable development during the COVID-19 pandemic was an ML model by Tsai <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</sup> designed to stratify high risk patients presenting to the emergency department (ED). This AI approach selected patients requiring ECGs for further diagnosis with an AUC of 0.89, demonstrating the role of AI in identifying high-risk individuals requiring necessary diagnostic attention. AI can stratify patients based on their risk of developing specific cardiac conditions by analyzing ECG data and other patient information. For instance, rECHOmmend, an ML model was developed to predict various structural abnormalities and cluster high-risk individuals. Trained on datasets from multiple sources, including ECGs from MUSE, Epic electronic health records, and echocardiograms from Xcelera, this model achieved an AUC of 0.91 with demographic details and ECGs as input<sup>[<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</sup>. AI models can be leveraged to predict the likelihood of future cardiac events, such as heart attacks or strokes, enabling healthcare providers to implement preventive measures and tailor monitoring and treatment plans individual risk profiles. This approach of personalized treatment not only enhances patient care but also improves the efficiency of healthcare delivery.</p><p>Moreover, AI ECG systems contribute to increase efficiency and accuracy in healthcare setting with their predictive capabilities. They can process large ECG datasets rapidly with higher accuracy, reducing the workload for clinicians and minimizing the risk of human error. For example, Akbilgic <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</sup> developed a CNN model to predict risks for heart failure (HF) solely from 12-lead ECGs with an AUC of 0.818, demonstrating comparable accuracy to conventional approaches such as FHS and ARIC risk calculators. Additionally, in HF patients with implanted cardiac sensors, ML technique can predict risk factors for rehospitalization<sup>[<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]</sup>. These systems provide valuable diagnostic support, offering insights and recommendations based on extensive datasets and evidence-based algorithms. The model developed by Raghunath <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]</sup> could predict all-cause mortality within one year from 12-lead ECGs with an AUC of 0.85, even when the ECGs were declared normal by cardiologists. By integrating data from various sources, including electronic health records (EHRs), wearable devices and other diagnostic tests, these systems provide a comprehensive risk assessment. Continuous learning from new data allows AI models to improve their predictive capabilities over time, ensuring that the insights they provide are up-to-date and accurate.</p></sec><sec><title>Comparative analysis of different AI models</title><p>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref> compares various AI models discussed in this review.
<table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Compares various AI-models in terms of their strengths, limitations, and suitability</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AI model</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strengths</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limitations</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suitability</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1D-CNN</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Efficient for time-series data, high accuracy in beat detection</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited spatial feature extraction, requires large datasets</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single-lead or short-term ECG analysis</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GRNN</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good generalization, works with small datasets</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Computationally expensive, poor scalability.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small datasets or specific beat classification tasks.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNN</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Robust feature extraction, High accuracy in multi-lead analysis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Computationally expensive, prone to overfitting</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-lead, large-scale ECG datasets, complex diagnosis.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNN (LSTM/GRU)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excellent for temporal sequence modeling, captures long-term dependencies.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High computational cost</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long-term ECG analysis, sequential data like continuous monitoring for arrhythmia.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deep belief networks (DBN)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Can learn hierarchical features, good for semi-supervised learning.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Requires large datasets, slow training and limited scalability.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tasks involving ECG feature extraction, useful in cases with both labeled and un-labeled data.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ensemble models</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Combines strengths of multiple models, high accuracy and robustness.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-computational cost, slow inference due to multiple models.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex, multi-class ECG classification.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SVM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strong generalization, works well for small datasets.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited to binary classification, less effective for large datasets.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small datasets or binary classification tasks like distinguishing between normal and abnormal ECG signals.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STA-CRNN</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Combines spatial and temporal attention for higher accuracy, robust to noisy data.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex to train, computationally expensive</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suitable for multi-class ECG classification, especially arrhythmia detection in noisy or large-scale datasets</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec><title>Navigating real-world implementation challenges and ethical issues</title><p>Although AI has made significant progress in ECG analysis, real-world implementation of AI-ECG systems poses numerous challenges, including computational demands, integration into existing healthcare systems, and the need for appropriate training of healthcare providers.</p></sec><sec><title>Computational requirements:</title><p>AI models, particularly deep learning techniques like CNNs and RNNs, require significant computational resources, posing challenges in clinical environments, especially for real-time ECG analysis<sup>[<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</sup>. Training these models, particularly on large multi-lead ECG datasets, demands high processing power, often necessitating GPU acceleration. In real-time settings like ICUs or wearable devices, low-latency inference is crucial, but many healthcare facilities lack the necessary advanced hardware. Moreover, continuous monitoring using AI can increase energy costs, straining resources, especially in low- and middle-income countries. Solutions such as deploying models closer to the data source, and using techniques like model pruning and quantization, help reduce computational demands and enable deployment on less powerful hardware<sup>[<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Integration into healthcare system</title><p>One of the hurdles to AI adoption in clinical settings is the difficulty in integrating AI models into existing healthcare systems, including electronic health records (EHRs) and medical devices. Healthcare systems are often built using platforms with varying levels of standardizations and compatibility. Integrating AI models into such systems requires ensuring that they can seamlessly interface with different data formats and communication protocols<sup>[<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]</sup>. For instance, an AI system for ECG interpretation must be compatible with EHR systems to use patients&#x02019; data and add diagnostic results automatically. Moreover, AI models need to be compatible with existing medical devices such as Holter monitors, and wearable devices, which often use proprietary data formats<sup>[<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]</sup>. Lack of standardization across device manufacturers can impede the integration of AI-driven solutions. Also, AI models rely on large datasets for training and continuous improvement. However, accessing and sharing patient ECG data across institutions is often restricted due to privacy regulations such as HIPAA in United States and GDPR in Europe, creating barrier to AI implementation. These hurdles can be overcome by ensuring that AI models are built to comply with healthcare data exchange standards like HL7 (Health level 7) and FHIR (Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources) which is crucial facilitating communication between different healthcare systems. Additionally, use of application programming interfaces (APIs) and intermediary solutions can bridge the gap between AI models and existing healthcare systems, enabling smoother data exchange<sup>[<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>&#x0201c;Black-Box&#x0201d; AI algorithms</title><p>The implementation of AI in clinical settings also requires training healthcare professionals, i.e., physicians, nurses and other healthcare staff that may be unfamiliar with AI technologies leading to skepticism or improper use. Physicians are often hesitant to trust AI systems, especially when models function as &#x0201c;black boxes&#x0201d; without offering clear explanations<sup>[<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]</sup>. Clinicians must be reluctant to rely on AI-based diagnostic tools if they cannot easily understand how the model arrived at a particular diagnosis. This lack of transparency, especially in DL models, raises concerns about the accountability in cases of misdiagnosis or errors. This question needs to be addressed &#x0201c;Who is responsible when an AI model makes a mistake?&#x0201d;</p><p>Implementation of AI literacy programs for healthcare professionals is essential. Training should focus on helping clinicians understand the strengths and limitations of AI models, how to interpret AI-driven results, and how to integrate these results into their clinical decision-making process. Additionally, the development of explainable AI tools can help address the &#x0201c;black box&#x0201d; issue by making AI model decisions more interpretable for healthcare professionals. Providing clinicians with user-friendly interfaces that clearly present AI outputs, along with confidence scores and visual explanations of the part of ECG that led to a particular classification, can improve trust and usability. Encouraging human-AI collaboration rather than full reliance on AI can build clinician trust. AI systems designed as decision support tools rather than autonomous diagnostic tools, where the final decision still rests with the healthcare provider, will allow clinicians to use AI as &#x0201c;second opinion&#x0201d; without feeling that their role is diminished. Moreover, collaborations of AI experts, data scientists and clinicians will boost the integration of AI in clinical workflow<sup>[<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Regulatory and ethical challenges</title><p>AI models for clinical use must meet stringent regulatory requirements for approval such as those set by the FDA (Food and Drug Administration) or the European Medicines Agency (EMA). Working closely with regulatory bodies during the development of AI systems can help streamline the approval process. This would also ensure that AI tools are built in compliance with safety standards and are validated through robust clinical trials. Ensuring data privacy in AI models that process patient information is a major concern. In addition to complying with privacy regulations, hospitals must also guard against cyberattacks that could compromise patient data and AI systems<sup>[<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Noises in ECG datasets</title><p>Noise can be effectively handled with a combination of preprocessing techniques and noise-resilient model architectures. Preprocessing involves techniques such as bandpass filtering, which removes high- and low-frequency noises, by breaking down the ECG signals into different frequency components, filtering out noise at specific levels. Independent component analysis is another method that helps isolate the true ECG signals from noise, particularly useful when analyzing data from multiple ECG leads. In addition to pre-processing, noise-robust AI models are designed to handle noisy input data more effectively. Ensemble models, which combine multiple algorithms such as CNNs (for spatial analysis) and LSTMs (for temporal patterns), offer a more comprehensive analysis by balancing the strengths of each model. This makes them more resilient to the inconsistencies caused by noise. Furthermore, attention mechanisms embedded in these models help focus the AI&#x02019;s analysis on the most relevant parts of the ECG signals, essentially filtering out noisy segments by selectively highlighting the important features for diagnosis.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec><title>Training dataset generalizability limitations</title><p>Most of the AI algorithms are trained on limited ECG datasets obtained from electronic healthcare records of one institute or more institute of a city or a country. This may limit the generalizability of the algorithms and lead to algorithm bias. Therefore, there is the need for preparation of diversified databases available for everyone to ensure generalizability in the AI algorithm being developed in every corner of the world<sup>[<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Multi-modal AI systems</title><p>Most of the AI-ECG systems are developed on ECG input but incorporation of risk indicators, demographics, and other tests as additional input improves the performance of the AI systems. Therefore, multimodal AI models must be developed for accurate diagnosis and personalized treatment plans<sup>[<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The applications of AI-ECG have seen remarkable advancements in recent years. DL models like CNN have not only enabled automated detection and classification of several cardiac abnormalities but also outperformed cardiologists. AI can detect AFib, AFL, VTA, LVH, MI, ALVD, etc., with high accuracy and also identify high-risk individuals and predict cardiac adverse events from multiple lead ECGs. However, there are still challenges to address before widespread clinical implementation including improved interpretability, diversified training datasets, cost effectiveness evaluation. Overall, AI-ECG systems hold promise to improve the efficiency, accuracy and sensitivity of ECG interpretations to guide screening and personalized management of cardiac abnormalities. More research is required to develop robust and generalizable AI algorithms to integrate into clinical workflow. Close collaboration between cardiologists, data scientists and software engineers will be key to realizing AI&#x02019;s full potential in advance cardiac care.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="equal"><p>Published online 9 January 2025</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent</title><p>Informed consent was not required for this review article.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Source of funding</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest disclosure</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contribution</title><p>Conceptualization &#x00026; Supervision: S.N.Q, M.I.; data curation: I.U. &#x00026; M.R.; resources: M.I. Validation: M.I. &#x00026; S.N.Q.; writing &#x02013; original draft: S.N.Q. &#x00026; I.U. &#x00026; M.R., M.K., G.A.K., R.N., R.S.A.; writing &#x02013; editing &#x00026; reviewing: S.N.Q.; final draft: All authors approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Research registration unique identifying number (UIN)</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Guarantor</title><p>Sardar Noman Qayyum.</p></sec><sec><title>Assistance with the study</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec><title>Presentation</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p>Not commissioned, externally peer-reviewed.</p></sec><sec><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>None.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bajwa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Munir</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Artificial intelligence in healthcare: transforming the practice of medicine</article-title>. <source>Future Healthc J</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e188</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34286183</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pianykh</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Langs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Continuous learning AI in radiology: implementation principles and early applications</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>297</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32840473</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macr&#x000ec;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D&#x02019;Albis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D&#x02019;Albis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The role and applications of artificial intelligence in dental implant planning: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Bioengineering</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>778</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39199736</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elkhader</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elemento</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Artificial intelligence in oncology: from bench to clinic</article-title>. <source>Semin Cancer Biol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33915289</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The emerging role of artificial intelligence enabled electrocardiograms in healthcare</article-title>. <source>BMJ Med</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>2</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjmed-2022-000193</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alzubaidi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Humaidi</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Review of deep learning: concepts, CNN architectures, challenges, applications, future directions</article-title>. <source>J Big Data</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33816053</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nabil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bereksi Reguig</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ectopic beats detection and correction methods: a review</article-title>. <source>Biomed Signal Process Control</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Devecioglu</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kiranyaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Real-time patient-specific ECG classification by 1D self-operational neural networks</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Biomed Eng</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1788</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>801</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34910628</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>High-performance personalized heartbeat classification model for long-term ECG signal</article-title>. <source>IEEE J Mag IEEE Xplore</source>
<year>2024</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7428848" ext-link-type="uri">https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7428848</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>UR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hagiwara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A deep convolutional neural network model to classify heartbeats</article-title>. <source>Comput Biol Med</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28869899</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dealing with noise problem in machine learning data-sets: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Procedia Comput Sci</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>161</volume>:<fpage>466</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kp</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>KK</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Classification of ECG beats using deep belief network and active learning</article-title>. <source>Med Biol Eng Comput</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29651694</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maindarkar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Viswanathan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Economics of artificial intelligence in healthcare: diagnosis vs</article-title>. <source>Treatment Healthcare</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2493</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36554017</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Exarchos</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsipouras</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Exarchos</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A methodology for the automated creation of fuzzy expert systems for ischaemic and arrhythmic beat classification based on a set of rules obtained by a decision tree</article-title>. <source>Artif Intell Med</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17543512</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sehrawat</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maanja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Artificial Intelligence for the detection and treatment of atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>Arrhythmia Electrophysiol Rev</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e12</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attia</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noseworthy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lopez-Jimenez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An artificial intelligence-enabled ECG algorithm for the identification of patients with atrial fibrillation during sinus rhythm: a retrospective analysis of outcome prediction</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2019</year>; <volume>394</volume>: <fpage>861</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31378392</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raghunath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ulloa-Cerna</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Deep neural networks can predict new-onset atrial fibrillation from the 12-lead ECG and help identify those at risk of atrial fibrillation-related stroke</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>143</volume>:<fpage>1287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33588584</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kotb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Artificial intelligence for ventricular arrhythmia capability using ambulatory electrocardiograms</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J - Digit Health</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>384</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38774363</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabut</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>BSP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Detection of ventricular arrhythmia using hybrid time&#x02013;frequency-based features and deep neural network</article-title>. <source>Phys Eng Sci Med</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33417159</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>ECG-based multi-class arrhythmia detection using spatio-temporal attention-based convolutional recurrent neural network</article-title>. <source>Artif Intell Med</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>101856</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32593390</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of 27 abnormalities from multi-lead ECG signals: an ensembled SE_resnet framework with sign loss function</article-title>. <source>Physiol Meas</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>065008</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Abnormality classification from electrocardiograms with various lead combinations</article-title>. <source>Physiol Meas</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>074002</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haseena</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>fuzzy clustered probabilistic and multi layered feed forward neural networks for electrocardiogram arrhythmia classification</article-title>. <source>J Med Syst</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20703571</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>EYK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Automated diagnosis of arrhythmia using combination of CNN and LSTM techniques with variable length heart beats</article-title>. <source>Comput Biol Med</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>278</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29903630</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An effective LSTM recurrent network to detect arrhythmia on imbalanced ECG dataset</article-title>. <source>J Healthc Eng</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>6320651</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31737240</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hannun</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rajpurkar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haghpanahi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cardiologist-level arrhythmia detection and classification in ambulatory electrocardiograms using a deep neural network</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30617320</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Usefulness of machine learning-based detection and classification of cardiac arrhythmias with 12-lead electrocardiograms</article-title>. <source>Can J Cardiol</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32585216</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olgin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Avram</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Performance of a convolutional neural network and explainability technique for 12-lead electrocardiogram interpretation</article-title>. <source>JAMA Cardiol</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34347007</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bisignani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rordorf</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Implantable cardiac monitors: artificial intelligence and signal processing reduce remote ECG review workload and preserve arrhythmia detection sensitivity</article-title>. <source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1343424</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38322767</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fiorina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maupain</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gardella</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of an ambulatory ECG analysis platform using deep neural networks in routine clinical practice</article-title>. <source>J Am Heart Assoc</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e026196</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36073638</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quartieri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marina-Breysse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pollastrelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Artificial intelligence augments detection accuracy of cardiac insertable cardiac monitors: results from a pilot prospective observational study</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Digit Health J</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36310681</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Left ventricular hypertrophy detection using electrocardiographic signal</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>2556</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36781924</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attia</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kapa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lopez-Jimenez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Screening for cardiac contractile dysfunction using an artificial intelligence&#x02013;enabled electrocardiogram</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30617318</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Artificial intelligence algorithm for screening heart failure with reduced ejection fraction using electrocardiography</article-title>. <source>ASAIO J</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>314</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33627606</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attia</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dugan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prospective evaluation of smartwatch-enabled detection of left ventricular dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>2497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>503</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36376461</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grogan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lopez-Jimenez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen-Shelly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Artificial intelligence-enhanced electrocardiogram for the early detection of cardiac amyloidosis</article-title>. <source>Mayo Clin Proc</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>2768</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34218880</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Deep learning-based algorithm for detecting aortic stenosis using electrocardiography</article-title>. <source>J Am Heart Assoc</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e014717</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32200712</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Myoung</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akkus</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Artificial intelligence for detecting mitral regurgitation using electrocardiography</article-title>. <source>J Electrocardiol</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32146201</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>H&#x000f6;ckmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Performance of a convolutional neural network derived from an ECG database in recognizing myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>8445</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32439873</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>[40]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development and validation of an artificial intelligence electrocardiogram recommendation system in the emergency department</article-title>. <source>J Pers Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>700</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35629122</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>[41]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ulloa-Cerna</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>RECHOmmend: an ECG-based machine learning approach for identifying patients at increased risk of undiagnosed structural heart disease detectable by echocardiography</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>146</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35533093</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>[42]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akbilgic</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karabayir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>ECG-AI: electrocardiographic artificial intelligence model for prediction of heart failure</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J - Digit Health</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>626</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34993487</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>[43]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stehlik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmalfuss</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bozkurt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Continuous wearable monitoring analytics predict heart failure hospitalization</article-title>. <source>Circ Heart Fail</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e006513</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32093506</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>[44]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raghunath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ulloa Cerna</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of mortality from 12-lead electrocardiogram voltage data using a deep neural network</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>886</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32393799</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>[45]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nygren</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Challenges to implementing artificial intelligence in healthcare: a qualitative interview study with healthcare leaders in Sweden</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34974828</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>[46]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karalis</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The integration of artificial intelligence into clinical practice</article-title>. <source>Appl Biosci</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>[47]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qayyum</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rehan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>AI integration in sjpgis care: a step towards improved health and quality of life outcomes</article-title>. <source>Ann Med Surg</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>2411</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>[48]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical significance, challenges and limitations in using artificial intelligence for electrocardiography-based diagnosis</article-title>. <source>Int J Arrhythmia</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36212507</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>[49]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiljer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hakim</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Developing an artificial intelligence-enabled health care practice: rewiring health care professions for better care</article-title>. <source>J Med Imaging Radiat Sci</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>S8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31791914</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>[50]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eche</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mokrane</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Toward generalizability in the deployment of artificial intelligence in radiology: role of computation stress testing to overcome underspecification</article-title>. <source>Radiol Artif Intell</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e210097</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34870222</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>[51]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multimodal multi-instance learning for long-term ECG classification</article-title>. <source>Knowl-Based Syst</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>270</volume>:<fpage>110555</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>