<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MS9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Medicine and Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2049-0801</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40109641</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11918691</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MS9.0000000000002855</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AMSU-D-24-02049</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00015</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Series</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Beyond convention: non-compacted myocardium, ventricular tachycardia, and systolic dysfunction in dextrocardia patients: a case series</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nazarenko</surname><given-names>Natalia</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>nmykhailiuuk@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Maliha</surname><given-names>Maisha</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>maishamaliha004@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cerna</surname><given-names>Luis</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>luis.cerna@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abittan</surname><given-names>Nathaniel</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>nathaniel.abittan@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Borkowski</surname><given-names>Pawel</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>pawel.borkowski.md@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Csecs</surname><given-names>Ibolya</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>ibolyacsecs@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>Mario</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>mariogar@montefiore.org</email><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>e</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Medicine, Jacobi Medical Center/AECOM, Bronx, New York</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Medicine, Dhaka Medical College, Dhaka, Bangladesh</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Cardiology, George Washington University, Washington, District of Columbia</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Cardiology, Westchester Medical Center, Bronx, New York</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Cardiology, Montefiore Medical Center, Bronx, New York</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Department of Medicine, Dhaka Medical College, Secretariat Rd, ABC Crescent Court, New Eskaton, Dhaka, 1000 Bangladesh. E-mail: <email>maishamaliha004@gmail.com</email> (M. Maliha).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>87</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0</ext-link> (CCBY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ms9-87-056.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Noncompaction of the left ventricle (LVNC) is linked to a higher risk of sudden cardiac death and stroke. Its prevalence ranges from 0.014% to 1.3% in the general population, rising to 7.5% in patients with dextrocardia.</p></sec><sec><title>Case summary:</title><p>A male in his late 70s presented with worsening dyspnea and leg swelling, with dextrocardia and frequent extrasystoles. Imaging revealed right-sided pleural effusion, severely reduced ejection fraction, and ventricular and atrial dilatation. He developed sustained monomorphic VT, was treated with amiodarone, had successful coronary stenting, and received an ICD with no further hospital readmissions or ICD events. A second case involved a male in his late 50s who presented with dyspnea. He had dextrocardia with situs inversus, subsegmental pulmonary embolism, and LVNC. He was treated with enoxaparin, medical therapy, and Holter monitoring, which showed mild arrhythmias. He declined ICD placement but remained event-free during the first year of follow-up.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion:</title><p>LVNC is a rare condition resulting from abnormal myocardial development during embryogenesis, leading to a two-layered myocardial structure. Diagnosis is based on imaging criteria. LVNC is linked to arrhythmias, heart failure, and conduction abnormalities, requiring interventions such as ICD placement, arrhythmia monitoring, and genetic testing. Further research is needed on genetic associations and long-term outcomes in dextrocardia patients.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><p><fig position="float" id="GA1"><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-056-g001" position="float"/></fig>
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>case series</kwd><kwd>dextrocardia</kwd><kwd>genetic cardiomyopathy</kwd><kwd>heart failure with reduced ejection fraction (HFrEF)</kwd><kwd>left ventricular noncompaction (LVNC)</kwd><kwd>monomorphic ventricular tachycardia (VT)</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The incidence of left ventricular noncompaction (LVNC) among patients with dextrocardia surpasses that in individuals with a physiologically normal heart position by approximately 6%<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup>. The etiology of LVNC is associated with a disrupted compaction process during embryogenesis, leading to the formation of deep intertrabecular recesses between the abnormal trabeculations<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup>. LVNC is linked to a genetic predisposition in 40% of instances, more prevalent in men than in women, and marked by a range of clinical phenotypes, including congenital heart diseases due to various gene penetrations<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup>. Among clinical manifestations, the most frequent include heart failure, thromboembolic events, and arrhythmias, particularly ventricular tachyarrhythmias<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup>.<boxed-text id="box1" position="float"><caption><title>Highlights</title></caption><p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>LVNC is more prevalent in individuals with dextrocardia, presenting significant risks such as heart failure and life-threatening arrhythmias. Awareness of this association can guide interventions like ICD placement and GDMT initiation.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Diagnosis of LVNC relies on specific imaging criteria identifying abnormal trabeculations and non-compacted myocardium.</p></list-item><list-item><p>LVNC has a genetic predisposition and may warrant genetic testing in patients with cardiomyopathy and dextrocardia.</p></list-item></list></p></boxed-text>
</p><p>The prevalence of LVNC is observed to be elevated in individuals with dextrocardia and situs inversus compared to those with a typical heart position. This case series aims to raise awareness within the medical community regarding the heightened likelihood of LVNC in patients with dextrocardia. Additionally, it aims to illustrate how LVNC can present as heart failure and, notably, as silent yet life-threatening ventricular tachycardia, necessitating fundamental changes in the treatment approach.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Cases description</title><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case #1</title><p>A male patient in his late 70s presented with worsening shortness of breath on exertion and lower extremity swelling lasting for 2 months. His medical history included dextrocardia and frequent extrasystoles. On physical exam, he had lung crackles, significant jugular venous distention, and 2+&#x000a0;pitting edema in his lower extremities. Vital signs were: blood pressure 94/81&#x000a0;mmHg, heart rate 53&#x000a0;bpm, respiratory rate 19, and oxygen saturation 95%. Blood tests showed an elevated B-type natriuretic peptide (BNP) at 1387&#x000a0;pg/mL (normal&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;250). A chest X-ray revealed right-sided pleural effusion and confirmed dextrocardia.</p><p>Shortly after the initial evaluation, he developed palpitations and sustained monomorphic ventricular tachycardia (VT) with a heart rate of 180&#x000a0;bpm was observed (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). He was treated with amiodarone and guideline-directed medical therapy (GDMT) for acute heart failure. An echocardiogram showed a severely reduced left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) of 35%, moderate left ventricular hypokinesis, moderate right ventricular enlargement, and severe dilation of both atria. Diagnostic heart catheterization revealed a 90% blockage in the middle right coronary artery, which was treated with a drug-eluting stent. A cardiac MRI confirmed dextrocardia and showed hyper-trabeculated left ventricular segments with severely reduced LVEF at 30% and right ventricular enlargement (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>EKG. (1) Sinus rhythm with premature atrial and ventricular contractions. Extreme right axis deviation and poor R wave progression suggest dextrocardia. EKG. (2) Monomorphic sustained ventricular tachycardia. Left bundle branch block, inferior axis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-056-g002" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Cardiac MRI. Images (A, D) Hypertrabeculation in anatomical LV (short axis). Images (B, C) Hypertrabeculations are in the mid-apical part (sagittal localizer image).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-056-g003" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>Given the known arrhythmogenic risk, a dual-chamber implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD) was placed as secondary prevention. He was discharged on daily amiodarone, dual antiplatelet therapy, and GDMT for heart failure with reduced ejection fraction (HFrEF). Follow-up visits showed no ICD events or hospital readmissions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case #2</title><p>A male patient in his late 50s presented with 1 day of shortness of breath, chest tightness, and cough. He reported no past medical history and had not sought medical care for decades. Physical exam showed mild respiratory distress with significant bilateral wheezing. His vital signs were: heart rate 101&#x000a0;bpm, blood pressure 140/100&#x000a0;mmHg, and oxygen saturation 95%. Blood tests revealed normal troponin levels and pro-BNP at 151&#x000a0;pg/mL (normal 1&#x02013;125). An ECG showed a regular sinus rhythm, extreme right axis deviation, and poor R-wave progression in the anterior leads (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>(<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>)).<fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>EKG. (1) Sinus rhythm, extreme right axis deviation with poor R waves progression in anterior leads, suggestive of dextrocardia. Holter. (2) Episode of non-sustained VT (31 beats) captured on Holter monitoring.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-056-g004" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>A chest CT angiography was done to rule out pulmonary embolism, which showed dextrocardia with situs inversus, a subsegmental pulmonary embolism, and a markedly hypoplastic right pectoralis muscle. He was started on enoxaparin. An echocardiogram showed moderate left ventricular hypokinesis with an LVEF of 35% and increased trabeculations in the left ventricular apex. Heart catheterization showed no coronary artery disease. Cardiac MRI showed a dilated left ventricle with an LVEF of 35%, biventricular hypokinesis, and a non-compacted to compacted myocardium ratio of 5:1 without late gadolinium enhancement (Fig. <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Cardiac MRI. Image (A) Hypertrabeculation in anatomical LV (sagittal localizer image). Images (B&#x02013;F) Hypertrabeculation is more apparent in the mid-apical part (short axis bSSFP cine images).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-056-g005" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>GDMT was started, and he was discharged with 14-day Holter monitoring, which later showed two episodes of supraventricular tachycardia, 0.72% premature ventricular beats, and two episodes of non-sustained ventricular tachycardia (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>(<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>)). ICD placement was offered as secondary prevention, but the patient declined due to follow-up limitations. During the first year of follow-up, he had no hospital readmissions or cardiac events.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>LVNC is a rare heart condition caused by developmental disturbances in the myocardium during early embryogenesis, leading to insufficient compaction of heart muscle fibers. First described by Grant in 1926, LVNC is characterized by a two-layered heart muscle structure: a thin compacted layer and prominent trabeculations with inter-trabecular recesses<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup>. The American Heart Association (AHA) classifies LVNC as a genetic cardiomyopathy, while the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the World Health Organization (WHO) label it as a familial/genetic unclassified cardiomyopathy<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup>. The estimated prevalence of LVNC in the general population is between 0.014% and 1.3%. However, Martinez <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> studied 172 individuals with heterotaxy and found LVNC in 13 patients (7.5%), indicating a higher occurrence in heterotaxy patients<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Specific diagnostic criteria for LVNC are still debated. In 2001, Jenni <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> suggested transthoracic echocardiography criteria based on a non-compacted to compacted myocardium ratio&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;2.0 in end-systole. Petersen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic><sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> proposed criteria for cardiac MRI (CMR), stating a non-compacted to compacted myocardium ratio&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;2.3 in diastole, with 86% sensitivity and 99% specificity. Captur <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> measured LV trabeculations using CMR and noted that patients with LVNC had a fractal dimension&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;1.3, compared to 1.2 in healthy individuals, suggesting higher accuracy with this method<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup>. In 2013, Stacey <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> analyzed excessive trabeculations with a cutoff noncompaction-to-compaction ratio of&#x000a0;&#x02265;2.0 in 122 participants<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>LVNC subtypes include (a) benign LVNC (35% of cases), with normal LV function and no significant arrhythmias; (b) dilated LVNC, characterized by reduced LV function; (c) hypertrophic LVNC, with diastolic dysfunction and high systolic function; (d) hypertrophic-dilated LVNC, with higher mortality and metabolic issues, mainly in children; (e) restrictive LVNC, marked by atrial enlargement and diastolic dysfunction with arrhythmia risk; (f) Right ventricular or biventricular LVNC, with spongiform RV appearance; and (g) LVNC associated with congenital heart disease. LVNC can have various inheritance patterns, including autosomal recessive, autosomal dominant, X-linked, and mitochondrial<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup>. Although most cases involve sarcomere- or cytoskeleton-related gene mutations, some, such as SCN5A, are linked to arrhythmias<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup>. In heterotaxy syndrome, genes like ZIC3, LEFTYA, CRYPTIC, and ACVR2B are affected, although a link between these and LVNC has not been established<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>LVNC is associated with conduction issues, life-threatening arrhythmias, thromboembolic events, and heart failure<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup>. A 20-year study involving 242 children found that 33.1% had arrhythmias, correlating with higher mortality (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> =&#x000a0;0.002). Ventricular tachycardia (VT) occurred in 17.4% of cases, leading to resuscitated sudden cardiac death in some, and 6.2% experienced sudden cardiac death<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup>. In a study of 960 patients, Kovacevic-Preradovic <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> identified LVNC as the cause of heart failure in 2% of cases<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup>. A systematic review of 135 LVNC cases with ventricular arrhythmias found that most originated in the non-compacted myocardium<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup>. Recently, Peterson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> proposed changing the term LVNC to &#x0201c;excessive trabeculations,&#x0201d; suggesting that high trabeculations might not have independent prognostic value without clinical suspicion of an inherited condition, with risk more closely linked to low LVEF and myocardial injury<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Decision-making in these cases was challenging due to the complex and overlapping clinical features of LVNC, dextrocardia, and situs inversus, which presented significant diagnostic and treatment hurdles. The lack of standardized diagnostic criteria for LVNC, along with evolving understanding of its clinical implications, made identifying and confirming the condition difficult. Furthermore, the patients&#x02019; structural abnormalities &#x02013; such as severe ventricular dilation, arrhythmogenic substrate, and reduced ejection fraction &#x02013; demanded precise assessment of arrhythmia risk and heart failure management strategies. The variability in clinical presentations, from heart failure symptoms to silent but life-threatening ventricular tachycardia, required nuanced judgment in implementing therapies like GDMT and determining whether invasive interventions, such as ICD placement, were warranted. Additionally, genetic considerations complicated decision-making, as the potential familial and heritable aspects of LVNC necessitated careful long-term planning, including family screening and preventive strategies. In the absence of prospective cohort data for such unique cases, clinicians had to balance immediate therapeutic needs with the potential long-term risks of heart failure and arrhythmia, highlighting the intricate nature of managing LVNC in patients with dextrocardia.</p><p>Our case series found an association between reduced LVEF and ventricular tachycardia in patients with LVNC and dextrocardia with situs inversus. This highlights the increased prevalence of noncompaction in individuals with dextrocardia and its possible link with ventricular arrhythmias and reduced LVEF. Awareness of these associations may prompt interventions such as genetic testing, arrhythmia monitoring, ICD placement, or GDMT initiation. Prospective data is needed to confirm these links and explore the genetics of cardiomyopathies and trabeculation disorders for better patient care.</p><p>Future criteria for studying and managing LVNC in patients with dextrocardia and situs inversus should prioritize integrating advanced imaging techniques like cardiac MRI to refine diagnostic accuracy, especially by addressing anatomical complexities. Emphasis should be placed on genetic testing to identify familial or heritable links, with a focus on sarcomere-related and heterotaxy-associated gene mutations. Clinical protocols could include stratifying patients based on LVEF and arrhythmia risk, guiding interventions like ICD placement or GDMT. Prospective data collection should explore how structural anomalies, such as ventricular dilation or excessive trabeculations, correlate with outcomes like heart failure and arrhythmias. Additionally, familial screening and long-term follow-up can provide insight into disease progression and inform preventive strategies.</p><p>The work has been reported as being in line with the PROCESS criteria.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup></p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors received no specific support or assistance for this work.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal"><p>Published online 9 January 2025</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent</title><p>Informed consent was obtained from all participants in this case series.</p></sec><sec><title>Sources of funding</title><p>This research received no external funding.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contribution</title><p>N.N., made substantial contributions to resources, software, supervision, visualization, writing &#x02013; original draft, writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing; M.M., made substantial contributions to resources, software, visualization, writing &#x02013; original draft, writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing; L.C., N.A., P.B., involved in writing &#x02013; original draft, writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing; I.C., involved in writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing; M.G., involved in supervision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest disclosure</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec><title>Research registration unique identifying number (UIN)</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Guarantor</title><p>Natalia Nazarenko.</p></sec><sec><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p>Not commissioned, externally peer-reviewed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Souto</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faro</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dextrocardia with situs inversus associated with noncompaction cardiomyopathy</article-title>. <source>Arq Bras Cardiol</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>e33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24030083</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Towbin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jefferies</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cardiomyopathies due to left ventricular noncompaction, mitochondrial and storage diseases, and inborn errors of metabolism</article-title>. <source>Circ Res</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>838</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28912186</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerecke</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Engberding</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Noncompaction cardiomyopathy-history and current knowledge for clinical practice</article-title>. <source>J Clin Med</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10112457</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhaskaran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Virk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Electrophysiologic and electroanatomic characterization of ventricular arrhythmias in noncompaction cardiomyopathy: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33792994</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schamberger</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Noncompaction cardiomyopathy and heterotaxy syndrome</article-title>. <source>Prog Pediatr Cardiol</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29445263</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oechslin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Echocardiographic and pathoanatomical characteristics of isolated left ventricular noncompaction: a step towards classification as a distinct cardiomyopathy</article-title>. <source>Heart</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>666</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11711464</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Timperley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neubauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Left ventricular thrombi in a patient with left ventricular noncompaction in visualisation of the rationale for anticoagulation</article-title>. <source>Heart</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>e4</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15604311</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Captur</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muthurangu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quantification of left ventricular trabeculae using fractal analysis</article-title>. <source>J Cardiovasc Magn Reson</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23663522</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stacey</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>St Clair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of systolic and diastolic criteria for isolated LV noncompaction in CMR</article-title>. <source>JACC Cardiovasc Imaging</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>931</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23769489</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belmont</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohapatra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Towbin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular genetics of heterotaxy syndromes</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cardiol</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15096953</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Limeres</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oristrell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical risk prediction in patients with left ventricular myocardial noncompaction</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>643</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34384546</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brescia</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rossano</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pignatelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mortality and sudden death in pediatric left ventricular noncompaction in a tertiary referral center</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>2202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>08</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23633270</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovacevic-Preradovic</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jenni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oechslin</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Isolated left ventricular noncompaction as a cause for heart failure and heart transplantation: a single center experience</article-title>. <source>Cardiology</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>158</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18663296</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aung</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Excessive trabeculation of the left ventricle: JACC: cardiovascular imaging expert panel paper</article-title>. <source>JACC Cardiovasc Imaging</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>408</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36764891</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Agha</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sohrabi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <collab>for the PROCESS Group</collab>. <article-title>Preferred reporting of case series in surgery (PROCESS) 2023 guidelines</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>3760</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>