<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MS9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Medicine and Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2049-0801</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40109582</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11918700</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AMSU-D-24-01543</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MS9.0000000000002757</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00027</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Immunotherapy in gastrointestinal cancers: current strategies and future directions &#x02013; a literature review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>El Fil</surname><given-names>Serene</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uwishema</surname><given-names>Olivier</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>uwolivier1@ktu.edu.tr</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rizwan Ahmed</surname><given-names>Aisha</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ratnani</surname><given-names>Tanya</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>ratnanitanya98@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rupani</surname><given-names>Ameen</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>ameen.rupani93@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>e</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Mshaymesh</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><degrees>BSc</degrees><email>srh3719@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>f</sup>
</xref><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Research and Education, Oli Health Magazine Organization, Research and Education, Kigali, Rwanda</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Natural Sciences, School of Arts and Sciences, Lebanese American University, Beirut, Lebanon</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Jinnah Medical and Dental College, Karachi, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Chhattisgarh Institute of Medical Sciences, Bilaspur, India</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>International Higher School of Medicine, Bishkek, Kyrgyzstan</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Division of Natural Sciences, Faculty of Sciences, Haigazian University, Beirut, Lebanon</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Oli Health Magazine Organization, Research and Education, 250, Kigali, Rwanda. E-mail: <email>srh3719@gmail.com</email> (S. Mshaymesh).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>87</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0</ext-link> (CCBY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ms9-87-151.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction:</title><p>The National Cancer Institute defines the disease of &#x0201c;cancer&#x0201d; as a group of disorders in which aberrant cells proliferate uncontrollably and have the potential to infiltrate neighboring tissues. It is well established that cancer remains a significant etiology contributing to worldwide mortality. Gastrointestinal (GI) neoplasms are a type of cancer that affects the digestive system and adds to the total cancer burden. Conventionally, several therapies have been employed, such as radiation and chemotherapy; nevertheless, their adverse effects have prompted the need for an improved therapeutic alternative. Immunotherapy thus became a notable medium of treatment for several malignancies, including tumors of the GI tract.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>This comprehensive review seeks to provide insight on future directions and prospective therapies under development, as well as information regarding the present strategies utilized to mitigate one of the primary forms of cancer, GI cancer.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>A detailed analysis of the existing literature on GI cancers has been conducted. Several databases were employed to gather this information, mainly PubMed/MEDLINE. Different aspects of the disease were considered when searching the databases to provide a comprehensive review of the current and future strategies being incorporated to mitigate the negative consequences of this disease.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Many strategies are being used currently, and some are still under development. These comprise the usage of immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs), cytokine therapy, cancer vaccines, oncolytic viruses, and adoptive cell therapy. For instance, various monoclonal antibodies have been developed to inhibit the immunomodulatory effects of programmed death-1 and programmed death-1 ligand. There are also results of several clinical trials showing significant benefits and many changes are introduced to make the best of these strategies and minimize the challenges to group sizes. These challenges include overcoming the tumor&#x02019;s immunosuppressive environment, finding suitable predictive biomarkers, and reducing the adverse effects. Additionally, several novel immunotherapeutic approaches, such as chimeric antigen receptor T-cell (CAR-T) therapy, are being studied. In 2017, the US FDA approved the use of two CAR-T therapies, which marks a major milestone following extensive research and clinical trials. New approaches such as toll-like receptor-directed and helminth-based immunotherapies are being developed for the treatment of GI cancers as well. These therapies, along with targeted treatments, represent the future of immunotherapy in GI cancers.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Immunotherapy plays a significant role in the different types of GI cancers. However, optimizing these treatments will require overcoming barriers such as immune resistance, minimizing side effects, and improving the selection of patients through biomarkers. Continued research into these novel therapies and the mechanisms of immune modulation will be key to maximizing the therapeutic benefits of immunotherapy in the future.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>gastrointestinal (GI) cancer</kwd><kwd>immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs)</kwd><kwd>immunotherapy</kwd><kwd>personalized treatments</kwd><kwd>predictive biomarkers</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>SDC</meta-name><meta-value>T</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cancer is a generic word for a broader group of diseases that can alter any part of the human body, associated terminology with it are malignant tumors and neoplasms[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. One key feature of cancer is the accelerated production of abnormal cells that originate beyond their normal ability, which can occupy neighboring parts of the body and spread to other organs, the former process known as metastasis, the primary cause of death by cancer[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>Cancer is the foremost cause of mortality around the world, causing close to 10 million mortalities or nearly one in six deaths[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The most common are that of breast, lung, colon, rectum, and prostate cancers. One-third of cancer mortalities are accountable to the usage of tobacco, high body mass index, consumption of alcohol, low intake of fruits and vegetables indicating reduced dietary fiber, and physical inactivity[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Early detection of many cancers may be managed early with cost-effectiveness[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>The gastrointestinal (GI) tract is a 25-foot-long pathway that extends from the mouth to the anus[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Food eaten passes as a bolus through the esophagus and is processed in the stomach and small intestines to extract nutrients[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Ultimately, the waste is removed from the body through the colon and rectum[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Sometimes, a tumor may form in one of these organs post-change in DNA causing abnormal cells to undergo mitotic division[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This multifaceted in nature.</p><p>The most common types of GI cancers are esophageal, gastric, colorectal, pancreatic, and liver[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Other types are much less common, including those belonging to neuroendocrine and gastrointestinal stromal tumors alongside anal cancer[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>GI malignancies contribute to one in four cancer cases and one in three cancer mortalities worldwide[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. There is a significant change in incidence and mortality rates globally[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. For example, the incidence of gastric cancer (GC) has decreased but colorectal cancer (CRC) incidence has increased in formerly low incidence rate regions[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Additionally, the incidence of liver and pancreatic cancer has risen in certain high-income regions[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Prevention strategies include control of tobacco, alcohol, and obesity, immunizing the population against hepatitis-B virus infection, and screening for CRCs[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>Data from three databases, GLOBOCAN, Cancer Incidence in Five Continents, and the World Health Organization mortality database, demonstrated that the incidence and mortality trends for GI malignancies differed by geography[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In 2018, Asia accounted for the bulk of new cases (63%) and deaths (65%), with Europe and North America accounting for 26% and 23%, respectively[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Asia had higher rates of esophageal, gastric, and liver cancers, while Europe and North America had higher rates of colorectal and pancreatic cancers[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>In the realm of oncological intervention, various methods such as conventional radiotherapy and chemotherapy have been employed. However, these come with their own set of limitations. The limitations of conventional radiotherapy, chemotherapy, or both include the following: inaccurate and unsafe radiation delivery, lack of sensitivity, and the development of drug resistance during treatment<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup>. Other limitations involve reduced drug uptake, increased drug export, inactivation of the effective agent within cells, changes to the molecular target, increased activity of the target pathway, and appearance or stimulation of alternative pathways<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup>. Additionally, enhanced repair of drug-induced modifications in the target molecules and activation or inhibition of intracellular signaling pathways can result in an imbalance between apoptosis and survival of tumor cells<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup>. Furthermore, differences among primary malignant gastrointestinal tumors, the diversity of tissues from which metastatic cells may access the gut, inter-individual variability, and the potential for sensitivity or resistance to change during tumor evolution further complicate treatment<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Immunotherapy is another type of cancer treatment. It uses substances made by the body or synthetically to boost the immune system and assist the body in locating and destroying cancer cells[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Immunotherapy may treat many different types of cancer, alone or in combination with chemotherapy and/or other cancer therapeutic modalities[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In contrast to traditional therapies, immunotherapy is considered a targeted therapy, employing medication that targets cancer-specific genes, proteins, or the tissue environment that aids tumor growth and survival[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Cancer immunotherapy emphasizes the importance of understanding tumor immunology &#x02013; particularly the roles of tumor antigens and the immunosuppressive tumor microenvironment[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Many novel immunotherapy agents have been developed that effectively combat cancer. While many cytokine-based approaches and their derivatives have become treatments deemed the standard-of-care for a variety of malignancies, other immunotherapy approaches, such as most cancer vaccines and cell-based approaches, remain experimental[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Fortunately, many novel immunotherapeutic agents are being researched and tested in clinical trials, which will hopefully provide new effective treatments for patients living with relapsed or refractory malignancies.</p><p>This review aims to comprehensively analyze the current landscape of immunotherapy strategies for GI cancers. Furthermore, we will look toward the future, examining the potential advancements for immunotherapy in GI cancers. This review seeks to provide health care professionals and researchers with a current and insightful analysis of this rapidly evolving field.</p></sec><sec><title>Current strategies of immunotherapy for GI cancers</title><p>Immunotherapy-based regimens have revolutionized the management of recurrent or metastatic GI cancers. Recent evidence has identified many tumor cells escape cellular immunoediting using various mechanisms involving immune checkpoint proteins, cytokines, and antigens. Multiple novel approaches are utilized to inhibit immunomodulation in GI cancers<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>-<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup>.</p><sec><title>Immune checkpoint inhibitors</title><p>The stimulatory or inhibitory signals generated by the interaction of programmed death-1 (PD-1) and cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen-4 (CTLA-4) with their ligands found on the surface of antigen-presenting cells (APC) or tumor cells are blocked by immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs)[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>PD-1 is present on the surface of lymphoid cells. PD-1 attachment with its ligand (programmed death-1 ligand, PD-L1) on tumor cells results in the deactivation of previously activated lymphoid cells (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) (further discussed in future directions)[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Various monoclonal antibodies have been developed to inhibit the immunomodulatory effects of PD-1 and PD-L1 (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>; Supplementary Table 1, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/MS9/A667" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/MS9/A667</ext-link>). Similarly, CTLA-4 is found on the cell surface of both CD4-positive and CD8-positive lymphocytes and binds to co-stimulatory factors on APCs[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This interaction decreases interleukin-2 (IL-2) production and T-cell proliferation[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] (Table <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Binding between T-cells and cancer cell.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-151-g001" position="float"/></fig>
<table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Approved PD-1 in gastric cancer as per National Comprehensive Cancer Network guidelines[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agents</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pembrolizumab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unresectable or metastatic MSI-H or dMMR solid, TMB-H solid tumors, MSI-H/dMMR or TMB-H gastroesophageal tumors</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nivolumab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Advanced or metastatic gastric cancer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dostarlimab-gxly</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSI-H/dMMR gastric tumors</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>dMMR, mismatch repair deficient; MSI-H, microsatellite instability-high; PD-1, programmed death-1; TMB-H, tumor mutational burden-high.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>A meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials of patients diagnosed with metastatic gastric/gastroesophagojejunal adenocarcinoma revealed that the addition of PD-1 inhibitors and not PD-L1 inhibitors to standard treatment has superiority in terms of overall survival (OS) and progression-free survival (PFS)[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Furthermore, in patients with microsatellite instability-high (MSI&#x02010;H) disease, adjuvant ICIs have benefits (further discussed in future directions)[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Various meta-analyses have demonstrated the superiority of adjuvant ICIs over multiple combined modalities in terms of OS and PFS<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup>. However, treatment-related adverse events were more prevalent in ICI groups[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Another meta-analysis revealed that ICIs alone or in combination with chemotherapy have benefits in OS in Asians, patients with microsatellite instability-high (MSI-H), PD-L1, and tumor mutational burden (TMB-positive) advanced GC[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p></sec><sec><title>Cytokine therapy</title><p>Cytokines are molecular messengers of the immune system enabling immune cells to communicate over short distances. Cytokine therapy aids the host&#x02019;s immune cells to target and destroy cancer cells. Clinical research has focused on utilization of several cytokines for the treatment of GCs[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Roles of cytokines in immunity<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Roles of cytokines in immunity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Induction of immunological checkpoints</p></list-item><list-item><p>Induces the secretion of inhibitory factors such as IL-10 and TGF-&#x003b2;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Induces the expression of inhibitors such as TIM</p></list-item><list-item><p>Induces activation of immune-dampening cells, including Tregs and MDSC</p></list-item><list-item><p>Induces activation of intracellular suppressors of cytokine signaling (CIS and SOCS) proteins that terminate the CD4 T-cell immune response</p></list-item><list-item><p>Induces the proliferation of activated NK cells</p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>CD, cluster of differentiation; CIS, cytokine-inducible SH2-containing protein; IL-10, interleukin-10; MDSC, myeloid-derived suppressor cells; NK, natural killer cell; SOCS, suppressors of cytokine signaling; TGF-&#x003b2;, transforming growth factor beta; TIM, triosephosphate isomerase; Tregs, regulatory T-cells.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>Clinical research has pinpointed several cytokines, including interferon-alpha (IFN-&#x003b1;), IL-2, IL-12, IL-15, and IL-21, for potential use in cancer management. Nevertheless, none of these cytokines have gained approval as a primary therapy for managing GCs[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The combination of cytokine therapy and chemotherapy enhances immune cell functionality and quality of life, and extends survival period with fewer adverse events<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup>. Similarly, a clinical trial has demonstrated enhanced tumor-infiltrating T-cell activity in GCs, preventing surgery-induced lymphopenia, and improving survival outcomes through subcutaneous IL-2 administration preoperatively<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Cancer vaccines</title><p>Cancer vaccine is another novel immunotherapy in GI cancers, activating the immune response to tumor cells[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. To date, numerous cancer vaccines have been developed (Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The clinical trials have demonstrated that peptide vaccines are well-tolerated, showing delayed hypersensitivity and eliciting an approximately 75% positive response from cytotoxic T-lymphocytes (CTLs)<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup>. Similarly, gastrin-17 diphtheria toxoid, an immune-conjugated vaccine, combined with chemotherapy has improved survival outcomes in advanced GC and gastroesophageal cancer patients[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. A recent study has introduced a vaccine design approach aimed at creating an <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> vaccine against CRC[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The strategy involves targeting <italic toggle="yes">Fusobacterium nucleatum</italic>, a significant bacterial pathogen linked to the initiation and advancement of tumors. The vaccine specifically targets the <italic toggle="yes">F. nucleatum</italic> membrane protein known as fibroblast activation protein-2 (Fap2), which facilitates bacterial attachment to colon cells and initiates the recruitment of immune cells and tumorigenesis. By incorporating B-cell and T-cell epitopes of Fap2, the vaccine seeks to bolster both cell-mediated and humoral immune responses. This proposed vaccine shows promise as a therapeutic intervention for <italic toggle="yes">F. nucleatum</italic>-induced human CRC[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
<table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Types of cancer vaccines and stimulus</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaccine type</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stimulus</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell-based vaccines</td><td rowspan="6" align="left" colspan="1">Activation of innate immune cells</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dendritic cell vaccines</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole cell vaccines</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleic acid-based vaccine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA vaccines</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA vaccines</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Induced pluripotent stem cell-based vaccine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of vaccine components by immune cells</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">In situ</italic> cancer vaccine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Activation of immune cells in tumor microenvironment</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microbial vector vaccines:</td><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1">Direct activation of immune response</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viral-based vaccines</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteria-based vaccines</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptide vaccine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of peptide antigens</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exosome-based vaccine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Activation of dendritic cells</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec><title>Oncolytic viruses</title><p>Oncolytic virotherapies (OVTs) selectively target and destroy cancer cells while inducing a systemic antitumor immune response, transforming unresponsive &#x0201c;cold&#x0201d; tumors into responsive &#x0201c;hot&#x0201d; tumors<sup>[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</sup>. OVTs comprise a broad diversity of viruses both naturally cancer selective or can be genetically engineered<sup>[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</sup> (Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The effectiveness of OVTs depends on several factors, such as virus/host interaction, degree of innate immunity and inflammation induced, types of virus-induced cell death, tumor physiology and phenotype, cell surface immune markers, and expression of immunosuppressive factors[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Genetic engineering has enabled the manipulation of pathogenic viruses for safety purposes and the development of more personalized and targeted therapies[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].
<table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Types of oncolytic viruses<sup>[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</sup></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natural cancer selective</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genetically engineered</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parvoviruses, myxoma virus, Newcastle disease virus, reovirus, and Seneca valley virus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measles virus, poliovirus, vaccinia virus, adenovirus, herpes simplex virus, and vesicular stomatitis virus</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Ongoing clinical trials on immunotherapy in gastrointestinal cancer</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agents</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT number</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PD-1 inhibitors</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Nivolumab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT02872116, NCT03647969, NCT02743494, NCT03662659</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Pembrolizumab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT03221426</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTLA-4 inhibitors</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Ipilimumab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT02872116, NCT03647969</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDL-1 inhibitors</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Atezolizumab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT03421288</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Durvalumab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT04157985</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Avelumab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT04157985</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oncolytic viral therapy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Adenovirus therapy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT04111172, NCT03740256, NCT03544723</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Herpes simplex virus type 2 strain HG52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT03866525</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adoptive cell therapy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Epithelial cell adhesion molecule</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT03563326, NCT02725125</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Human epidermal growth factor receptor-2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT04650451, NCT03740256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT04348643</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Claudin18.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT04581473, NCT04404595</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Glypican-3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCT03198546</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>CTLA-4, cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen-4; PD-1, programmed death-1; PDL-1, programmed death-1 ligand.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>Jun <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. reveal that a novel genetically engineered vaccinia virus carrying the human sodium iodide symporter (hNIS) gene, GLV-1h153, can efficiently regress gastric tumors and allow deep-tissue imaging[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Experimental GI cancer models have shown that OVT administration enhances antitumor immunity and prolongs survival, but its safety and efficacy in humans remain inconclusive<sup>[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>-<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</sup>. Ongoing human clinical trials are listed in Table <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">5</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Adoptive cell therapy</title><p>Immune cells are isolated and collected via leukapheresis, genetically modified, expanded <italic toggle="yes">ex vivo</italic>, and administered back to the patient[<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The types of adoptive cell therapy (ACT) include tumor-infiltrating lymphocyte therapy, engineered T-cell receptor therapy, chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy (CAR-T) (further discussed in future directions), CAR-natural killer (NK) therapy, CAR-NK T therapy, CAR-macrophage (M) therapy, and CAR-&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T therapy[<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p><p>A phase 1 clinical trial revealed carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) CAR-T cells are well-tolerated in patients with CEA&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;colorectal liver metastasis[<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. However, first-generation CAR-T is associated with respiratory toxicity[<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Clinical trials are still ongoing to evaluate the safety and efficacy of ACT (Table <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).
</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Challenges in immunotherapy for GI cancers</title><p>While immunotherapy offers a promising new avenue for treating GI cancers, several hurdles must be overcome to maximize its effectiveness.</p><sec><title>Overcoming tumor immunosuppression</title><p>One major challenge lies in overcoming the tumor&#x02019;s immunosuppressive microenvironment.</p><p>Due to its unique mechanisms of action, it has been found that the mechanisms of immunotherapy resistance are different from those of conventional chemotherapy, and this requires a significant challenge that needs to be addressed[<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. These mechanisms are &#x0201c;complex and heterogeneous&#x0201d; and constitute a combination of many genes and metabolism<sup>[<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</sup> and can be divided into two different types: intrinsic and extrinsic<sup>[<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>-<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Intrinsic mechanisms are those that include the alterations in antitumor immune response pathways and changes in signaling pathways in tumor cells which in turn lead to the formation of an inhibitory immunosuppressive microenvironment<sup>[<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</sup>. On the other hand, extrinsic factors mostly include the ones that are linked to the local tumor microenvironment<sup>[<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Disabling these mechanisms is crucial to ensure a successful immunotherapy treatment and future research should focus on the strategies to overcome this resistance. One suggested strategy is developing combination therapies that can work to target these different resistance mechanisms and thus increase the efficiency of the treatment for patients[<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Identifying predictive biomarkers</title><p>Another challenge is identifying reliable and new biomarkers of GI cancers to predict which patients will benefit from immunotherapy and this allows them to choose the suitable therapeutic option and thus improve the outcomes<sup>[<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>In order for a biomarker to be valid, it should display several characteristics such as being present in high amounts in patients diagnosed with cancer while being absent or present in low quantities in unaffected patients[<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], being easily measured or evaluated<sup>[<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</sup>, and being able to provide information about the cancer in the patient<sup>[<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>A special type of biomarkers is known as &#x0201c;predictive biomarkers,&#x0201d; and these allow the prediction of the response that a patient will give for a certain treatment and thus define the subpopulation that will benefit from that specific therapy[<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p><p>Understanding the importance of these biomarkers is crucial and can change the staging of many GI cancers[<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Additionally, it is essential that clinicians understand the molecular biology behind GI cancers as they will be requesting biomarker testing as a part of the patient screening[<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Moreover, it is important to note that strategies for combining more than one biomarker are promising and can help improve the accuracy of the development of the treatment[<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].</p><p>For instance, new research has pinpointed several crucial genes linked to GI cancers, underscoring their potential as targets for therapy and as biomarkers. In CRC, the COL11A1 gene is excessively expressed and contributes to tumor advancement by upregulating other genes like THBS2, COL10A1, COL5A2, and COL1A2, thereby driving neoplasia[<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Its overexpression is tied to poor overall and disease-free survival, making it a promising biomarker for assessing CRC prognosis and a target for therapeutic intervention[<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In GC, Fam198b has been associated with tumor advancement and drug sensitivity, working through the Phosphatidylinositol 3-Kinase/Protein Kinase B (PKB)/B-Cell Lymphoma 2 (PI3K/AKT/BCL-2) signaling pathway[<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Its suppression significantly hinders tumor cell proliferation and migration, positioning Fam198b as a promising biomarker and a therapeutic target[<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Furthermore, RNF180 is being investigated as a new tumor suppressor, with potential clinical applications as a biomarker in GC[<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Together, these genes, among others, present important avenues for advancing GI cancer treatment, particularly in the context of immunotherapy, where targeting specific molecular pathways could improve patient outcomes and customize treatment strategies.</p></sec><sec><title>Adverse effects</title><p>Finally, adverse effects associated with immunotherapy are a concern.</p><p>Most patients who receive treatment &#x02013; particularly anti-CTLA-4 therapy &#x02013; suffer from aphthous ulcers, esophagitis, gastritis, diarrhea, and colitis<sup>[<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Thus, it is important that physicians familiarize themselves with these effects and remain in touch with the agent&#x02019;s providers in order to reduce these unwanted results[<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Future directions of immunotherapy for GI cancers</title><sec><title>Novel immunotherapeutic approaches</title><sec><title>Chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy</title><p>Chimeric antigen receptor T-cell treatment (CAR-T) involves modifying T-cells in such a way that they eventually can identify particular tumor cell surface antigens without needing the major histocompatibility complex[<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].</p><p>In the year 2017, the US FDA approved the usage of two CAR-T cell treatments, following years of extensive medical and laboratory research as well as targeted clinical trials<sup>[<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Recently, certain laboratories have attempted to utilize EphA2, a protein that is expressed on the surface of many cancer cells. CAR-T cells that recognize EphA2 have shown the ability to recognize and assault esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (ESCC) <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>[<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. These results provide a new direction for ESCC immunotherapy in the future[<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Coincidentally, liver and other GI malignancies have been successfully treated with CAR-T cell therapy.</p><p>Moreover, the human epidermal growth factor receptor-2 (HER2) gene is crucial for function in the incidence and progression of GC, which strongly produces the protein p185[<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Since p185 is negatively expressed in healthy individuals, it may be a prime candidate for CAR-T cell-based anticancer therapy[<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].</p><p>Additionally, it has been discovered that CAR-T cell treatment for GI tumors can effectively target CEA, a sensitive tumor biomarker[<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. As a result, many studies have been conducted on the management of various malignancies, including pancreatic cancer, liver cancer, and cholangiocarcinoma. The integration of CAR-T cell therapy with targeted treatments, including those that target CEA, HER2, Glypican-3, Mucin 1 (MUC1), cluster of differentiation (CD133), epithelial cell adhesion molecule, or epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) has demonstrated significant promise in combination treatment<sup>[<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>-<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Microsatellite instability-high</title><p>Microsatellite instability-high (MSI-H), a predictive predictor of immunotherapy response rates, is frequently brought on by the MMR gene deficiency.</p><p>The effectiveness of ICIs in solid tumor patients appears to be associated with MSI, according to mounting data. The phase III KEYNOTE062 trial found that pembrolizumab with chemotherapy did not show a better median OS compared to chemotherapy alone in patients with PD-L1 combined positive score (CPS) of 1 or greater or PD-L1 CPS of 10 or greater[<xref rid="R60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. This trial was conducted as the first-line therapy for advanced GC.</p><p>A comparison of the median overall survival (mOS) of patients with MSI-H tumors revealed that pembrolizumab with chemotherapy outperformed treatment with chemotherapy alone in terms of survival benefit[<xref rid="R60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>].</p><p>It is very critical that MSI-H and PD-L1 are not confused together. While both are important biomarkers for selecting patients, PD-L1 only measures the number of cancer cells that can block the immune response when bound to PD-1. However, MSI-H reveals a high number of mutations due to MMR. In patients with MSI-H tumors, regardless of their PD-L1 level, adding pembrolizumab to chemotherapy significantly improved OS compared to chemotherapy alone. Thus, MSI-H has emerged as a stronger biomarker, especially for patients with GC.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunotherapy combined with VEGF/VEGFR inhibitors</title><p>Promising clinical activity was observed in a multicenter phase I/II study of nivolumab with paclitaxel plus ramucirumab (Supplementary Table 1, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/MS9/A667" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/MS9/A667</ext-link>) as a second-line therapy[<xref rid="R61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Compared to patients with lower PD-L1 levels (CPS&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;1), those with higher levels (CPS&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;1) had a longer median survival time (13.8 vs. 8.0&#x000a0;months) (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In a different phase I/II trial (NIVORam), the objective response rate (ORR) was 26.7% and the mOS was 9.0&#x000a0;months when nivolumab was the only medication used in conjunction with ramucirumab as a second-line treatment for advanced GC[<xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). No direct comparison between the two aforementioned clinical studies can be established because PD-L1 expression in patients in the NIVORam study was not assessed; however, it is plausible that paclitaxel may be omitted as a second-line medication. Nivolumab also demonstrated a strong response rate (ORR: 44%) and median PFS (5.6&#x000a0;months) when paired with regorafenib[<xref rid="R61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>/Supplementary Table 1, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/MS9/A667" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/MS9/A667</ext-link>).
<fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>PD-L1 expression and efficacy of Nivolumab-based combination therapies for second-line advanced GC.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-151-g002" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>Durvalumab plus ramucirumab also demonstrated safety by the established characteristics of the individual therapies. These findings suggest that vascular endothelial growth factor/vascular endothelial growth factor receptor (VEGF/VEGFR) inhibitor combinations may be useful treatment plans for advanced GC.</p><p>In addition to VEGF/VEGFR, ICIs may be used in conjunction with other targeted treatments. A secreted antagonist, Dickkopf-1 (DKK1), binds to the Wnt co-receptor LRP5/6 and causes cells to become desensitized to common Wnt ligands[<xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). DKK1 thus inhibits the Wnt signaling pathway, which is involved in cell proliferation and survival and is abnormally activated in cancer cells making cells less responsive to these signals.
<fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Wnt signaling pathway regulation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-151-g003" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>Patients with advanced GC were treated with pembrolizumab and a neutralizing antibody against DKK1 in an early-stage trial called DKN-01[<xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. DKK1 high patients showed an objective reaction of 50%, but DKK1 low patients showed no objective response. Additionally, DKK1 high patients showed prolonged PFS and OS.</p></sec><sec><title>Dual ICI strategy</title><p>For GC, a combination of anti-PD-1 and anti-CTLA-4 has also been investigated. Nivolumab was investigated as monotherapy or in combination with ipilimumab (Supplementary Table 1, <ext-link xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/MS9/A667" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/MS9/A667</ext-link>) in patients with advanced or metastatic solid tumors in the CheckMate-032 trial[<xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. The OS of these two groups was comparable (6.9 vs. 6.2&#x000a0;months) for metastatic and chemotherapy-refractory esophagogastric cancer, despite the combination group (nivolumab 1 mg/kg&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;ipilimumab 3 mg/kg) having a higher ORR than the nivolumab monotherapy group (24% vs. 12%)[<xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Nonetheless, it appears that combination therapy is more beneficial in the PD-L1-positive and MSI-H categories (18-month survival: 50% for the combination group vs. 13&#x02013;29% for the nivolumab monotherapy group).</p><p>It is anticipated that nivolumab in conjunction with ipilimumab will take center stage as a third-line treatment for GC.</p><p>For MSI-H advanced GC or esophagogastric junction cancer, a phase II study (NO LIMIT) combining nivolumab and low-dose ipilimumab is now being conducted as the first-line therapy[<xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>TLR-directed immunotherapy</title><p>Toll-like receptors (TLRs) are crucial components of the innate immune system. They function as pattern recognition receptors that detect pathogen-associated molecular patterns and initiate immune responses<sup>[<xref rid="R66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>-<xref rid="R69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]</sup>. So far, 10 human and 13 murine TLRs have been identified[<xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. TLRs are present in different types of cells, including innate immune system components such as macrophages, neutrophils, dendritic cells, NK cells, and mast cells[<xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. They are also found in adaptive immune system cells like T and B lymphocytes, as well as stromal cells[<xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].</p><p>In addition to immune cells, TLRs are widely expressed in different types of tumor cells. They regulate tumor growth and function, directly or indirectly, as a &#x0201c;double-edged sword&#x0201d;[<xref rid="R66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. They play complex roles in tumor immunity, with either protumor, antitumor, or dual effects[<xref rid="R68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. When TLRs interact with a specific molecule, they greatly increase the presence of various signaling molecules on the cell surface, triggering the release of cytokines and the activation of T-cells[<xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].</p><p>Specific TLRs have been implicated in the progression of GI cancers. For example, in esophageal cancer, increased expression of TLR3, TLR4, TLR7, and TLR9 has been linked to esophageal squamous cell carcinomas, while TLR1, TLR2, TLR4, and TLR6 are often overexpressed in esophageal adenocarcinoma[<xref rid="R68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Similarly, in GC, TLR2, TLR3, TLR4, TLR5, TLR7, and TLR9 are all implicated in influencing the advancement of tumors[<xref rid="R68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Notably, increasing expression levels of TLR2, 4, 5, and 9 have been associated with cancer progression from normal gastric mucosa to pre-cancerous lesions, gastric dysplasia, and ultimately to gastric adenocarcinoma[<xref rid="R68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. TLRs may have a particular function in the development of GC, as indicated by their increased expression[<xref rid="R68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Another study also found that TLR9 is significantly involved in the progression of GC[<xref rid="R69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].</p><p>TLRs&#x02019; capability to propagate immunity makes them attractive targets for the expansion of numerous immunotherapeutic approaches that target cancer[<xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. One of the methods involves utilizing TLR ligands/agonists either on their own or as part of combined treatment approaches[<xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. These substances are considered immune-boosting elements that amplify TLR signaling and activate an innate immune response resulting in long-lasting adaptive immunity[<xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Several TLR agonists have shown significant efficacy in advanced clinical trials<sup>[<xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,<xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]</sup>. For example, dSLIM, a TLR9 agonist, is used for metastatic CRC[<xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Additionally, combination therapy involving TLR9 agonists and ICIs has demonstrated promising effects in clinical studies[<xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].</p><p>TLR-targeted immunotherapy presents a comprehensive approach to treating GI cancers by utilizing the body&#x02019;s natural immune responses. The various functions of TLRs in both promoting and inhibiting tumors emphasize the importance of understanding their signaling pathways in different cancer scenarios. Ongoing exploration of TLR-mediated mechanisms is essential for developing precise treatments that effectively mobilize the immune system against GI malignancies. The advancing field of TLR-targeted therapies not only shows potential for improving cancer treatment outcomes but also offers valuable insights into the complex relationship between immune responses and tumor biology.</p></sec><sec><title>Helminth-based immunotherapy</title><p>Helminth-based immunotherapy has emerged as a novel approach in the context of GI cancers. For instance, one research indicates that helminth-derived products, such as those from <italic toggle="yes">Taenia crassicjpg</italic>, can enhance the efficacy of conventional treatments like 5-fluorouracil (5FU) by modulating immune responses and promoting apoptosis in tumor cells, particularly in CRC[<xref rid="R71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. To illustrate, <italic toggle="yes">T. crassicjpg</italic> molecules have been shown to downregulate pro-inflammatory cytokines and markers associated with malignancy, while promoting NK cell activity and recruitment[<xref rid="R71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. In another research study, it was found that mice infected with <italic toggle="yes">T. crassicjpg</italic> had 60% fewer colon tumors compared to uninfected mice[<xref rid="R72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Additionally, 50% of the infected mice did not develop any tumors at all. The impressive outcome was linked to reduced involvement of inflammatory monocytes and the suppression of intensified inflammatory reactions within the colon[<xref rid="R72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Conversely, certain helminths, like <italic toggle="yes">Heligmosomoides polygyrus</italic>, may exacerbate inflammation and tumor development when introduced during the early phases of colitis-associated colon cancer, highlighting the complexity of helminth interactions with cancer pathology[<xref rid="R73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Therefore, the role of helminths in either promoting or delaying the onset of colon cancer has not been fully understood[<xref rid="R71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].</p><p>Given these findings, helminth-based immunotherapy represents a novel and promising approach for treating GI cancers. However, careful consideration is needed due to the complex and context-dependent effects of different helminth species on tumor progression and inflammation.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Personalized immunotherapy</title><p>Previous literature has shown that patients who have the same phenotype of a tumor do not respond the same to a particular immunotherapeutic treatment[<xref rid="R74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. This urges that the molecular basis of the tumor needs to be studied for every patient and then allow targeted immunotherapy to be used in such cases. Personalized immunotherapy is very critical as it considers each patient to be an independent group, and this allows every patient to receive a treatment method tailored toward his case only[<xref rid="R74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. One of the methods of providing personalized treatment is through classifying the tumors based on mutations in genes like MMR, DNA Polymerase Epsilon, and Rat Sarcoma Viral Oncogene Homolog[<xref rid="R74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. This can be done through next-generation sequencing or other methods (bioinformatic technologies[<xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]) that identify those mutations, especially those that create neoantigens. Neoantigens are novel antigens that are generated by cancer cells due to various causes including genomic mutations[<xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. These antigens are classified as non-self and trigger an immune response[<xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Thus, early identification and prediction of these neoantigens[<xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] can allow for the designing of personalized immunotherapy<sup>[<xref rid="R74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,<xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]</sup>, including cancer vaccines[<xref rid="R74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. However, this neoantigen-based personalized immunotherapy is currently costly and consumes time to identify the specific neoantigen and assemble the vaccine[<xref rid="R74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>].</p><p>For instance, a phase II clinical trial investigated a personalized neoantigen-based peptide vaccine in combination with chemotherapy for the treatment of CRC[<xref rid="R76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. The vaccine induced a cellular immune response in 63% of patients and a humoral response in 49%[<xref rid="R76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Moreover, the median OS was 498&#x000a0;days and the 1-year and 2-year survival rates were 53% and 22%, respectively[<xref rid="R76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. These results suggest that personalized neoantigen-based peptide vaccines have the potential to improve clinical outcomes for CRC patients.</p><p>Personalized immunotherapy is not limited to neoantigen cancer vaccines. Indeed, many other approaches have shown great results such as ACT ones. However, the cost of such treatment remains a barrier. Future research and clinical trials should focus on personalized methods that are cost-effective and that can be performed in a faster time.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>One important treatment for many malignancies, including GI tumors, is immunotherapy. While radiation and chemotherapy remain the mainstays of cancer treatment, immunotherapy is gaining ground as a valuable adjunct therapy due to its potential to target tumors more precisely and with fewer side effects. However, its position as a primary treatment is not yet established because there are still many challenges to overcome. For instance, the tumor&#x02019;s immunosuppressive microenvironment often limits the effectiveness of immune-based therapies. Future research should aim to address these challenges by investigating how to modulate the tumor microenvironment to allow better immune cell infiltration and activity.</p><p>Several key areas of research could significantly advance the field. First, ICIs like anti-PD-1/PD-L1 and anti-CTLA-4 have shown promise but are not universally effective. Future studies should explore combination therapies that can enhance the efficacy of ICIs, such as pairing them with chemotherapy, radiation, or other immunotherapies. Additionally, understanding biomarkers that predict patient responses to ICIs is critical to tailoring treatments to individuals. TLR agonists are another promising area. These molecules can activate innate immune responses and have the potential to be used in combination with ICIs or other immunotherapies to improve outcomes. More research is needed to assess the safety and efficacy of TLR agonists in GI cancers specifically. Helminth-based immunotherapies, while still in the early stages, offer a novel approach by modulating the immune system to suppress inflammation or enhance tumor-fighting responses. Investigating helminth-derived molecules and their ability to work alongside conventional treatments like 5FU should be a focus of future research. Moreover, identifying and validating reliable biomarkers to predict patient responses to various forms of immunotherapy remains a crucial area of study. This will enable more personalized treatments and reduce unnecessary side effects for patients unlikely to respond to certain therapies.</p><p>In conclusion, while immunotherapy holds great potential, its future success will depend on further research into combination therapies, overcoming immune resistance, and making the treatments more accessible and affordable. With more focused studies on ICIs, TLR agonists, helminth-based approaches, CAR-T cell therapy, cancer vaccines, oncolytic viruses, and biomarkers, immunotherapy could move from an adjunct therapy to a cornerstone in the fight against GI cancers.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Selected artwork shown in the <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figs. (1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) were used from pictures provided by Servier Medical Art (Servier; <ext-link xlink:href="https://smart.servier.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://smart.servier.com/</ext-link>), licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported License. Also, we would like to thank Oli Health Magazine Organization (OHMO) members for their contributions and support for this manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>All co-authors approved the final manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>All co-authors have read and approved the submission.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Supplemental Digital Content is available for this article. Direct URL citations are provided in the HTML and PDF versions of this article on the journal&#x02019;s website, <ext-link xlink:href="www.lww.com/annals-of-medicine-and-surgery" ext-link-type="uri">www.lww.com/annals-of-medicine-and-surgery</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal"><p>Published online 9 January 2025</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Ethics approval</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Sources of funding</title><p>We have not received any financial support for this manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contribution</title><p>O.U.: Conceptualization, project administration, writing &#x02013; review and designing, and reviewed and edited the final draft. S.E.F.: Writing &#x02013; review and designing and reviewed and edited the first draft. All authors contributed to data collection and assembly, manuscript writing, and final approval of manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest disclosure</title><p>No conflicts of interest declared.</p></sec><sec><title>Research registration unique identifying number (UIN)</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Guarantor</title><p>Olivier Uwishema; principal investigator (PI).</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p>Not commissioned, externally peer-reviewed.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Gastrointestinal cancers</collab>. <article-title>Yale Medicine</article-title>. <year>2022</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.yalemedicine.org/conditions/gastrointestinal-cancers" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.yalemedicine.org/conditions/gastrointestinal-cancers</ext-link>. Accessed May 31, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Gastrointestinal cancers global burden</collab>. <article-title>Cancer.gov</article-title>. <year>2020</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://dceg.cancer.gov/news-events/news/2020/global-burden-gastro" ext-link-type="uri">https://dceg.cancer.gov/news-events/news/2020/global-burden-gastro</ext-link>. Accessed May 31, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abnet</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global burden of 5 major types of gastrointestinal cancer</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>159</volume>:<fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>349.e15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32247694</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <article-title>Global burden of gastrointestinal cancers</article-title>. <year>2020</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://gco.iarc.fr/stories/gastro-intestinal/" ext-link-type="uri">https://gco.iarc.fr/stories/gastro-intestinal/.</ext-link> Accessed May 31, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <article-title>Cancer</article-title>. February 2022. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/cancer" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/cancer.</ext-link> Accessed May 31, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>JJG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blazquez</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Importance and limitations of chemotherapy among the available treatments for gastrointestinal tumours</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Agents Med Chem</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19199863</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Benefits and challenges of radiation therapy in gastric cancer: techniques for improving outcomes</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Cancer Res</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19343133</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Cancer.Net</collab>. <article-title>What is immunotherapy?</article-title>
<month>May</month>
<year>2022</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cancer.net/navigating-cancer-care/how-cancer-treated/immunotherapy-and-vaccines/what-immunotherapy#:%7E:text=Immunotherapy%20is%20a%20type%20of,and%2For%20other%20cancer%20treatments" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cancer.net/navigating-cancer-care/how-cancer-treated/immunotherapy-and-vaccines/what-immunotherapy#:~:text=Immunotherapy%20is%20a%20type%20of,and%2For%20other%20cancer%20treatments</ext-link>. Accessed May 31, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee Ventola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer immunotherapy, Part 1: current strategies and agents</article-title>. <source>P T</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28579724</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iranzo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Callejo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Assaf</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Overview of checkpoint inhibitors mechanism of action: role of immune-related adverse events and their treatment on progression of underlying cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Med (Lausanne)</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2022.875974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dougan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dranoff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dougan</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer immunotherapy: beyond checkpoint blockade</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Cancer Biol</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37539076</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Current status and future potential of predictive biomarkers for immune checkpoint inhibitors in gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>ESMO Open</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e000791</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32817133</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kundel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sternschuss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of immune&#x02010;checkpoint inhibitors in metastatic gastric or gastroesophageal junction adenocarcinoma by patient subgroups: a systematic review and meta&#x02010;analysis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Med</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>7613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32869544</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mahjoubfar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Azizi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immune checkpoint inhibitors plus chemotherapy versus chemotherapy alone as first-line therapy for advanced gastric and esophageal cancers: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Int Immunopharmacol</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>109317</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36252494</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Helali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>CHL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A meta-analysis with systematic review: efficacy and safety of immune checkpoint inhibitors in patients with advanced gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Oncol</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>908026</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36387109</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ajani</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D&#x02019;Amico</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bentrem</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gastric cancer, version 2.2022, NCCN clinical practice guidelines in oncology</article-title>. <source>J Natl Compr Canc Netw</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35130500</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conlon</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miljkovic</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waldmann</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cytokines in the treatment of cancer</article-title>. <source>J Interferon Cytokine Res</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29889594</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sckisel</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bouchlaka</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Monjazeb</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Out-of-sequence signal 3 paralyzes primary CD4+ T-cell-dependent immunity</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>240</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26231116</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Floros</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tarhini</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anticancer cytokines: biology and clinical effects of interferon-&#x003b1;2, interleukin (IL)-2, IL-15, IL-21, and IL-12</article-title>. <source>Semin Oncol</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26320059</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S-F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness and safety of chemotherapy combined with cytokine-induced killer cell /dendritic cell&#x02013;cytokine-induced killer cell therapy for treatment of gastric cancer in China: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Cytotherapy</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27421742</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of DC-CIK immunotherapy combined with chemotherapy on locally advanced gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>J Oncol</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>2022</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cesana</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caprotti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Preoperative IL-2 immunotherapy enhances tumor infiltrating lymphocytes (TILs) in gastric cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Hepatogastroenterology</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>634</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16995478</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Piacentini</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Franciosi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phase-II randomized study of preoperative IL-2 administration in radically operable gastric cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Hepatogastroenterology</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>1872</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15532847</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Recent progress and future perspectives of immunotherapy in advanced gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>948647</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35844558</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rha</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamaue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A phase I/Ib study of OTSGC-A24 combined peptide vaccine in advanced gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>332</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29587677</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shomura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immunological evaluation of peptide vaccination for patients with gastric cancer based on pre&#x02010;existing cellular response to peptide</article-title>. <source>Cancer Sci</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>802</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>08</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12967479</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ajani</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Randolph Hecht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An open&#x02010;label, multinational, multicenter study of G17DT vaccination combined with cisplatin and 5&#x02010;fluorouracil in patients with untreated, advanced gastric or gastroesophageal cancer : the GC4 study</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>1908</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16568451</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>PSS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cell surface fibroblast activation protein-2 (Fap2) of fusobacterium nucleatum as a vaccine candidate for therapeutic intervention of human colorectal cancer: an immunoinformatics approach</article-title>. <source>Vaccines (Basel)</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>525</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36992108</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oncolytic virus: a catalyst for the treatment of gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Oncol</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1017692</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36505792</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiocca</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rabkin</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oncolytic viruses and their application to cancer immunotherapy</article-title>. <source>Cancer Immunol Res</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>300</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24764576</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>K-W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oncolytic virotherapy</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>658</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22781695</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cattaneo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miest</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shashkova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Reprogrammed viruses as cancer therapeutics: targeted, armed and shielded</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18552863</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gholami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>T-J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A novel oncolytic viral therapy and imaging technique for gastric cancer using a genetically engineered vaccinia virus carrying the human sodium iodide symporter</article-title>. <source>J Exp Clin Cancer Res</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24383569</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tazawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Functional remodeling of intraperitoneal macrophages by oncolytic adenovirus restores anti-tumor immunity for peritoneal metastasis of gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther Oncol</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>200806</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38745748</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X-Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A recombinant measles virus vaccine strain rMV-Hu191 has oncolytic effect against human gastric cancer by inducing apoptotic cell death requiring integrity of lipid raft microdomains</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>460</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31226409</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shikano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kasuya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Combination of the tumor angiogenesis inhibitor bevacizumab and intratumoral oncolytic herpes virus injections as a treatment strategy for human gastric cancers</article-title>. <source>Hepatogastroenterology</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>1844</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22172413</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Odunsi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adoptive cell therapy for nonhematologic solid tumors</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>3397</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>407</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37104722</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phase I escalating-dose trial of CAR-T therapy targeting CEA+ metastatic colorectal cancers</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28366766</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thistlethwaite</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gilham</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guest</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The clinical efficacy of first-generation carcinoembryonic antigen (CEACAM5)-specific CAR T cells is limited by poor persistence and transient pre-conditioning-dependent respiratory toxicity</article-title>. <source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28660319</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>[40]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A new approach to overcoming resistance to immunotherapy: nanotechnology</article-title>. <source>Front Oncol</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1210245</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37637050</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>[41]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of cancer resistance to immunotherapy</article-title>. <source>Front Oncol</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1290</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32850400</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>[42]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Said</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer resistance to immunotherapy: comprehensive insights with future perspectives</article-title>. <source>Pharmaceutics</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1143</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37111629</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>[43]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlomagno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Incollingo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tammaro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnostic, predictive, prognostic, and therapeutic molecular biomarkers in third millennium: a breakthrough in gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Biomed Res Int</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>[44]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaili</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biomarkers for response to immune checkpoint inhibitors in gastrointestinal cancers</article-title>. <source>World J Gastrointest Oncol</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35116101</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>[45]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Badreddine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biomarkers in gastrointestinal cancers</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>2106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18637088</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>[46]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Exploring the differential expression and prognostic significance of the COL11A1 gene in human colorectal carcinoma: an Integrated bioinformatics approach</article-title>. <source>Front Genet</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>608313</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33597969</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>[47]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diallo</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fam198b as a novel biomarker for gastric cancer and a potential therapeutic target to prevent tumor cell proliferation dysregulation</article-title>. <source>Transl Oncol</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>101824</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37939629</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>[48]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>CNY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of the gene structure, functional significance, and clinical application of RNF180, a novel gene in gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>947</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21717426</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>[49]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kichloo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albosta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dahiya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Systemic adverse effects and toxicities associated with immunotherapy: a review</article-title>. <source>World J Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>150</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33767971</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>[50]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szabados</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Adverse effects and radiological manifestations of new immunotherapy agents</article-title>. <source>Br J Radiol</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>20180164</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30281331</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>[51]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadelain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brentjens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rivi&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The basic principles of chimeric antigen receptor design</article-title>. <source>Cancer Discov</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23550147</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>[52]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandlund</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Non-Hodgkin lymphoma across the pediatric and adolescent and young adult age spectrum</article-title>. <source>Hematology</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>2016</volume>:<fpage>589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27913533</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>[53]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Mansour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-Foheidi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of second-generation CAR T-cell therapy in diffuse large B-cell lymphoma: a meta analysis</article-title>. <source>Mol Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>[54]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>EphA2 chimeric antigen receptor-modified T cells for the immunotherapy of esophageal squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Dis</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2779</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29997940</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>[55]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>CAR-T cell therapy in gastrointestinal tumors and hepatic carcinoma: from bench to bedside</article-title>. <source>Oncoimmunology</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e1251539</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28123893</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>[56]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holzinger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abken</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>CAR T cells targeting solid tumors: carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) proves to be a safe target</article-title>. <source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1505</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>07</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28755091</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>[57]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Significantly increased anti&#x02010;tumor activity of carcinoembryonic antigen&#x02010;specific chimeric antigen receptor T cells in combination with recombinant human IL&#x02010;12</article-title>. <source>Cancer Med</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>4753</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31237116</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>[58]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>EGLIF-CAR-T cells secreting PD-1 blocking antibodies significantly mediate the elimination of gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Manag Res</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>8893</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>902</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33061585</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>[59]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabernero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoff</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pertuzumab plus trastuzumab and chemotherapy for HER2-positive metastatic gastric or gastro-oesophageal junction cancer (JACOB): final analysis of a double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled phase 3 study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Oncol</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1372</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30217672</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>[60]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shitara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Cutsem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of pembrolizumab or pembrolizumab plus chemotherapy vs chemotherapy alone for patients with first-line, advanced gastric cancer. the KEYNOTE-062 phase 3 randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1571</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32880601</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>[61]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kadowaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Minashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multicenter phase I/II study of nivolumab combined with paclitaxel plus ramucirumab as second-line treatment in patients with advanced gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1029</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33262133</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>[62]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takahari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phase I/II study of ramucirumab plus nivolumab in patients in second-line treatment for advanced gastric adenocarcinoma (NivoRam study)</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>[63]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bothwell</surname><given-names>ALM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Canonical and non-canonical WNT signaling in immune cells</article-title>. <source>Trends Immunol</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>830</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30213499</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>[64]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klempner</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bendell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Villaflor</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>DKN-01 in combination with pembrolizumab in patients with advanced gastroesophageal adenocarcinoma (GEA): tumoral DKK1 expression as a predictor of response and survival</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>[65]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janjigian</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bendell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>CheckMaTE-032 study: efficacy and safety of nivolumab and nivolumab plus ipilimumab in patients with metastatic esophagogastric cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>2836</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30110194</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>[66]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>TLR-mediated metabolic reprogramming in the tumor microenvironment: potential novel strategies for cancer immunotherapy</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Immunol</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>428</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29553135</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>[67]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Application of toll-like receptors (TLRs) and their agonists in cancer vaccines and immunotherapy</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1227833</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37936697</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>[68]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Behzadi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Toll-like receptor-guided therapeutic intervention of human cancers: molecular and immunological perspectives</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1244345</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37822929</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>[69]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Majewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mertowska</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mertowski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>How toll-like receptor 9 plays a key role in the development of gastric cancer and is linked to Epstein&#x02013;Barr virus infection</article-title>. <source>Cancers (Basel)</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>5104</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37894471</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>[70]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pahlavanneshan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sayadmanesh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ebrahimiyan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Toll-like receptor-based strategies for cancer immunotherapy</article-title>. <source>J Immunol Res</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>2021</volume>:<fpage>9912188</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34124272</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>[71]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendoza-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Medina-Reyes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Barrera</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Helminth-derived molecules improve 5-fluorouracil treatment on experimental colon tumorigenesis</article-title>. <source>Biomed Pharmacother</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>175</volume>:<fpage>116628</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38663106</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>[72]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Callejas</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Saucedo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Terrazas</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Parasites as negative regulators of cancer</article-title>. <source>Biosci Rep</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>BSR20180935</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30266743</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>[73]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pastille</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frede</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McSorley</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal helminth infection drives carcinogenesis in colitis-associated colon cancer</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e1006649</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28938014</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>[74]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Personalized immunotherapy in colorectal cancers: where do we stand?</article-title>
<source>Front Oncol</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>769305</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34888246</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><label>[75]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neoantigens: promising targets for cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Signal Transduct Target Ther</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36604431</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><label>[76]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kibe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yutani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Motoyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phase II study of personalized peptide vaccination for previously treated advanced colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Immunol Res</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1154</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25351849</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>