<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MS9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Medicine and Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2049-0801</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40109627</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11918657</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MS9.0000000000002848</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AMSU-D-24-01343</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00009</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>FDA approval of crovalimab: a milestone in paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria treatment</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anwar</surname><given-names>Diya</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Asim Ali</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Hooriya</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rashmeen</surname><given-names>Syeda</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Farhat</surname><given-names>Solay</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shahnoor</surname><given-names>Syeda</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>e</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Abdul Moiz</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Ayub Medical College, Abbottabad, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Rawalpindi Medical University, Rawalpindi, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Jinnah Sindh Medical University, Karachi, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Faculty of Medical Sciences, Lebanese University, Beirut, Lebanon</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow University of Health Sciences, Karachi, Pakistan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Faculty of Medical Sciences, Lebanese University, Beirut, Lebanon E-mail: <email>solayfarhat@gmail.com</email> (S. Farhat).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>87</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0</ext-link> (CCBY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ms9-87-027.pdf"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p><italic toggle="yes">Dear Editor</italic>,</p><p>Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH) is a rare hematopoietic stem cell disorder characterized by hemolytic anemia, thrombosis, smooth muscle dystonia, and bone marrow failure. The global prevalence of PNH is as high as 38 individuals per million, with higher prevalence in certain Asian countries like Japan, Korea, and China compared to the West<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup>. PNH arises from a deficiency in complement inhibitors, specifically due to mutations in the phosphatidylinositol N-acetylglucosaminyltransferase subunit A (PIGA) gene, leading to the absence of glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI)-anchored proteins, such as CD55 and CD59, which protect red blood cells from complement-mediated destruction<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup>. The resulting uncontrolled complement activation causes intravascular hemolysis, releasing free hemoglobin that depletes nitric oxide, contributing to smooth muscle dystonia. Additionally, chronic hemolysis and complement overactivation trigger platelet activation and increase the risk of thrombotic events, while immune-mediated damage to hematopoietic stem cells can result in bone marrow failure<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>PNH symptoms vary widely and severely impact patients&#x02019; quality of life. Chronic destruction of red blood cells results in severe anemia, manifesting as fatigue, shortness of breath, and paleness<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup>. Patients frequently suffer from hemoglobinuria, which causes dark or hematic urine. Additionally, hemolytic anemia often necessitates multiple blood transfusions, which can elevate the risk of iron overload and associated complications<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup>. Bone marrow failure in PNH leads to pancytopenia, making patients more susceptible to infections, bruising, and bleeding<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup>. The combination of chronic hemolysis, frequent transfusions, and risks of thrombosis and bone marrow failure creates a significant physical and emotional burden, affecting overall quality of life<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup>.</p><sec><title>Current treatment options</title><p>Up until now, five drugs had received FDA approvals for treating PNH, either as add-on therapies or as various complement inhibitors: Eculizumab, <bold>Danicopan</bold>, Ravulizumab, Pegcetacoplan, and Iptacopan. Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> summarizes the details of these FDA-approved drugs for PNH.<table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of FDA approved drugs for Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Date of approval</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mode of administration</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical Trails</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eculizumab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">March, 2007</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C5 complement inhibitor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intravenously every 2 weeks</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 3 TRIUMPH Trial (NCT00122330) &#x00026; SHEPHERD Trial (NCT00130000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ravulizumab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">December, 2018</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C5 complement inhibitor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intravenously every 8 weeks</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 3 Trials (NCT02946463 &#x00026; NCT03056040)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pegcetacoplan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">May, 2021</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C3 complement inhibitor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subcutaneously twice weekly</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 3 PEGASUS trial (NCT03500549)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iptacopan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">December, 2023</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor B inhibitor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orally twice daily</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 3 APPLY-PNH trial (NCT04558918) &#x00026; APPOINT-PNH (NCT04820530)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Danicopan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">April, 2024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor D inhibitor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orally thrice daily</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 3 ALPHA trial (NCT04469465)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p>Eculizumab and Ravulizumab, both C5 inhibitors, block the terminal complement cascade by preventing C5 cleavage, inhibiting the formation of the membrane attack complex (MAC). While effective in reducing hemolysis and thromboembolic events, both require intravenous administration, with Ravulizumab offering less frequent dosing. Pegcetacoplan, a C3 inhibitor, prevents both intravascular and extravascular hemolysis but requires infection monitoring due to broader complement suppression. Danicopan, an oral factor D inhibitor, complements C5 inhibitors to prevent breakthrough hemolysis. Iptacopan, a factor B inhibitor, targets the alternative pathway, offering a more convenient oral option.</p><p>While effective in disease management, these treatments have notable shortcomings, such as incomplete complement inhibition, breakthrough hemolysis, inadequate control of bone marrow failure, and the risk of clonal evolution<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup>. Addressing these limitations requires the development of advanced complement inhibitors and improved drugs that offer comprehensive management of PNH, while also being easy to administer and practical.</p></sec><sec><title>Crovalimab: A promising new treatment option for PNH</title><p>Crovalimab is a new potential drug being explored to address the limitations of previously available treatments. In February 2024, it received initial approval in China for treating both adolescents and adults with PNH, followed by approval in Japan in March 2024<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup>. The latest development is the approval of Crovalimab-akkz (Piasky) by the FDA on 24 June 2024<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup>. Crovalimab, developed by Chugai Pharmaceutical in collaboration with Roche, is a humanized monoclonal antibody targeting complement component C5. It works by inhibiting complement C5, thereby hindering its transformation into C5a and C5b. This inhibition prevents the formation of the membrane attack complex (MAC) and reduces intravascular hemolysis<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical trials assessing crovalimab efficacy</title><p>The drug Crovalimab was approved after the Phase 3 COMMODORE 2 trial, which enrolled 204 PNH patients without prior disease-specific treatment<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup>. Of these, 135 patients received Crovalimab and 69 patients received Eculizumab, with 38.7% having a history of aplastic anemia and 5.9% myelodysplastic syndrome. Results showed that about two-thirds of the patients on Crovalimab therapy did not require any sort of further blood transfusions, and nearly 80% experienced no hemolysis. Most completed the 24-week treatment and entered the extension phase. This trial effectively demonstrates the non-inferiority of Crovalimab to the already established treatment, Eculizumab, in managing PNH. After the completion of trial, 84% of patients in the COMMODORE 2 trial expressed a preference for Crovalimab over Eculizumab. The primary reasons for this preference included the easier method of administration, fewer hospital visits required, and a shorter time needed to administer the treatment<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Likewise, the Phase 3 COMMODORE 3 trial from China showed that 78.7% of patients achieved hemolysis control, and 51% avoided transfusions<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup>. While common side effects included respiratory tract infections, infusion-related reactions, and type 3 hypersensitivity reactions, no treatment discontinuations occurred due to side effects in either trial, demonstrating Crovalimab&#x02019;s efficacy and tolerability. The COMMODORE 1 trial results also demonstrated a better safety profile for Crovalimab, providing sustained complement inhibition, disease control, and showing that 85% of patients preferred it over Eculizumab<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup>. The findings from clinical trials evaluating Crovalimab efficacy are outlined in Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of clinical trials evaluating Crovalimab efficacy.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trial</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of participants</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COMMODORE 1<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 3, randomized, multicentral trial</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crovalimab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eculizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crovalimab maintained robust complement activity inhibition, achieved disease control, with 85% patient preference over eculizumab.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COMMODORE 2<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 3, randomized, multicentral trial</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crovalimab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eculizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crovalimab matched eculizumab in controlling hemolysis and reducing transfusions, with fewer breakthrough events, and stabilized hemoglobin levels.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COMMODORE 3<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 3, single arm, multicentral trial</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crovalimab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crovalimab effectively controlled hemolysis in about 78.7% of patients and markedly decreased the requirement for transfusions compared to baseline.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec><title>Recommended dosage</title><p>Crovalimab represents the first complete treatment for PNH, administered monthly via subcutaneous injection, offering the convenience of self-administration at home. The prescribed dosing schedule starts with an initial 1000-1500 mg intravenous (IV) infusion on Day 1, followed by four weekly 340 mg subcutaneous injections on Days 2, 8, 15, and 22. The maintenance dose of 680-1020 mg, begins on Day 29 and is administered every 4&#x000a0;weeks via subcutaneous injection thereafter<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup>.</p><sec><title>Recommendations</title><p>This approval marks a significant breakthrough in hematological sciences and has the potential to transform the lives of patients suffering from PNH. Clinicians across the healthcare spectrum should be promptly informed about Crovalimab, ensuring they recognize it as a viable treatment option. With its promising efficacy, it is crucial that this drug is made available on a large scale to benefit as many patients as possible. Global accessibility will require partnerships between Roche and local health authorities to streamline distribution and integrate Crovalimab into national healthcare plans. Pricing strategies must ensure affordability and equitable access, especially in resource-limited settings. Collaborations with patient advocacy groups will be crucial for raising awareness, promoting timely diagnosis, and facilitating treatment access.</p><p>Additionally, treatment guidelines and policies need to be updated to include Crovalimab as a standard therapy option. Furthermore, training programs and workshops should be organized for healthcare providers to familiarize them with the administration and management of Crovalimab. Patient education initiatives are also essential to ensure adherence and optimize outcomes. However, while this approval is a milestone, we must continue to invest in research and development to further enhance treatment outcomes for those suffering from paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria, always striving for better patient care. Continued surveillance and real-world studies will be necessary to monitor long-term efficacy and safety, ensuring that the benefits observed in clinical trials translate effectively into everyday clinical practice.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>C5 inhibitors, including Crovalimab, have notable limitations, such as non-responsiveness in patients with C5 polymorphisms and breakthrough hemolysis triggered by infections or complement-amplifying conditions. Additionally, Crovalimab therapy may face challenges related to extravascular clearance due to C3b accumulation. Patients transitioning from other C5 inhibitors to Crovalimab are also at risk of developing Drug-Target-Drug Complexes (DTDCs), which could impact treatment effectiveness. Addressing these challenges will be essential to optimizing therapy and ensuring better outcomes for PNH management.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>PNH profoundly impacts patients with severe anemia, hemolysis, and heightened thrombotic risks, necessitating frequent transfusions and posing significant complications like iron overload and bone marrow failure. While current treatments have limitations, Crovalimab represents a promising advance with improved disease control, patient preference, and safety. Future studies should explore long-term efficacy, real-world outcomes, and comparative effectiveness. Research on personalized approaches, combination therapies, and global collaborations will be key to optimizing care and expanding access.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal"><p>Published online 9 January 2024</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Ethical approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not Applicable.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>Not Applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interest</title><p>The authors have no competing interests to declare.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>The authors did not receive any financial support for this work.</p></sec><sec><title>Research registration unique identification number (UIN)</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p>Not commissioned, externally peer-reviewed</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p><bold>Conceptualization of ideas</bold>: Abdul Moiz Khan and Diya Anwar</p><p><bold>Manuscript preparations</bold>: Abdul Moiz Khan, Syeda Shahnoor and Syeda Rashmeen.</p><p><bold>Writing of initial draft</bold>: Diya Anwar, Asim Ali Khan and Hooriya Ahmed.</p><p><bold>Review and Editing</bold>: Solay Farhat, Abdul Moiz Khan and Syeda Shahnoor.</p><p><bold>Final draft</bold>: All authors approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dingli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maciejewski</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larratt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Relationship of paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH) granulocyte clone size to disease burden and risk of major vascular events in untreated patients: results from the International PNH Registry</article-title>. <source>Ann Hematol</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>1637</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37199789</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Risitano</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rotoli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria: pathophysiology, natural history and treatment options in the era of biological agents</article-title>. <source>Biologics</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19707355</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dingli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lehrhaupt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The burden of illness in patients with paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria receiving treatment with the C5-inhibitors eculizumab or ravulizumab: results from a US patient survey</article-title>. <source>Ann Hematol</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34973099</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olutogun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cutini</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Notaro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Complement-mediated haemolysis and the role of blood transfusion in paroxysmal nocturnal haemoglobinuria</article-title>. <source>Blood Transfus</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25761313</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Ouqaili</surname><given-names>MTS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Musleh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-Kubaisi</surname><given-names>SMA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Depending on HPLC and PCR, detection of aflatoxin B1 extracted from Aspergillus flavus strains and it&#x02019;s cytotoxic effect on AFB treated-hematopoietic stem cells obtained from human umbilical cord</article-title>. <source>Asian J Pharm</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22377/ajp.v12i03.2650</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kulagin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klimova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rudakova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Benefits and limitations of long-term eculizumab treatment for Paroxysmal Nocturnal Hemoglobinuria (PNH): real-world data from large cohort study in Russia</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>132</volume>:<fpage>2589</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhillon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Crovalimab: first Approval</article-title>. <source>Drugs</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>707</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38740735</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>FDA approves crovalimab for paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria</article-title>. <year>2024</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.onclive.com/view/fda-approves-crovalimab-for-paroxysmal-nocturnal-hemoglobinuria" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.onclive.com/view/fda-approves-crovalimab-for-paroxysmal-nocturnal-hemoglobinuria</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000f6;th</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The complement C5 inhibitor crovalimab in paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>912</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31978221</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000f6;th</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phase 3 randomized COMMODORE 2 trial: crovalimab versus eculizumab in patients with paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria naive to complement inhibition</article-title>. <source>Am J Hematol</source>
<year>2024</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38884175/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38884175/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of the C5 inhibitor crovalimab in complement inhibitor-naive patients with PNH (COMMODORE 3): a multicenter, Phase 3, single-arm study</article-title>. <source>Am J Hematol</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>1407</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37421604</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheinberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cl&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phase 3 randomized COMMODORE 1 trial: crovalimab versus eculizumab in complement inhibitor-experienced patients with paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria</article-title>. <source>Am J Hematol</source>
<year>2024</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38924124/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38924124/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>