<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MS9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Medicine and Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2049-0801</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40109647</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11918724</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MS9.0000000000002815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AMSU-D-24-01651</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00059</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Unmasking pseudopelade of Brocq in male adult: a rare case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Usama Bin Shabbir</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>mohammadusamabin2000@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Afridi</surname><given-names>Faryal</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>faryalkhanafridi@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Waheed</surname><given-names>Aiman</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>amywaheed@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alvi</surname><given-names>Rafia</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>rafiaalvi5@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamza Gul</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS, MD</degrees><email>Hamzagul448@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wardak</surname><given-names>Abdul Baseer</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><email>a.baseer21@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Pakistan Institute of Medical Sciences, Islamabad, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Rawalpindi Medical University and Allied Hospitals, Rawalpindi, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Hayatabad Medical Complex, Peshawar, Pakistan</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Razia Bahlol Hospital, Kabul, Afghanistan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Razia Bahlol Hospital, Madina-Township Kabul, Afghanistan. Tel.: +93 79 542 1983. E-mail: (<email>a.baseer21@gmail.com</email>) (A. B. Wardak).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>87</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives License 4.0</ext-link>, which allows for redistribution, commercial and noncommercial, as long as it is passed along unchanged and in whole, with credit to the author.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ms9-87-380.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction and importance:</title><p>Pseudopelade of Brocq originally describes asymptomatic, irregularly shaped patches of atrophic hair loss. It designates a rare, idiopathic, slow progressive cicatricial alopecia without evident signs of folliculitis or inflammatory changes. This dermatological disorder still needs further research into its pathogenesis and treatment. We hope this case report provides valuable insight and a significant addition to the research gap as it is common in females but rare in male patients, and serves as a starting point for additional inquiry regarding causal link and epidemiology of disease.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation:</title><p>The authors present a rare case of Pseudopelade of Brocq in a male adult patient. The patient initially presented with progressive hair loss, but later examination revealed multiple atrophic patches of hair loss in the vertex area without any signs of inflammation. Subsequently, the patient was treated with corticosteroids and showed improvement in disease progression.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion:</title><p>The pathogenesis of the Pseudopelade of Brocq is not well defined. Diagnosing this clinical entity is challenging due to delayed presentation which leads to increased patient suffering, preventable complications like baldness, and economic burdens.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Pseudopelade of Brocq is a rare dermatologic manifestation. It is crucial to raise awareness among healthcare professionals regarding its delayed presentation to prevent its long-term complications.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>alopecia</kwd><kwd>case report</kwd><kwd>clinical</kwd><kwd>dermatology</kwd><kwd>pseudopelade of Brocq</kwd><kwd>treatment</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Pseudopelade of Brocq designates a rare, idiopathic, slow progressive cicatricial alopecia without evident signs of folliculitis or inflammatory changes[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Pseudopelade includes the end stage of various forms of scarring alopecia whereas pseudopelade of Brocq originally describes asymptomatic, irregularly shaped patches of atrophic hair loss mostly in white males. The disease progresses slowly with a random distribution of lesions commonly involving the scalp vertex. The classical presentation includes bald patches with &#x0201c;footprints in the snow&#x0201d; appearance which are white hypopigmented (porcelain) and depressed atrophic plagues[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This case highlights the importance of considering the pseudopelade of Brocq as a differential diagnosis in patients presenting with cicatricial alopecia. This dermatological disorder still needs further research into its pathogenesis and treatment. We hope this case report provides valuable insights and a significant addition to the research gap.</p></sec><sec><title>Methodology</title><p>This case report has been formulated based on the SCARE guideline checklist[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 21-year-old male, who works as a driver presented with a 2-year history of progressive hair loss affecting the vertex of the scalp. He had no history of systemic illness, trauma to the scalp, medication, smoking, alcohol consumption, or any other drug abuse history. No family member had similar complaints or symptoms. Physical examination revealed multiple, irregularly placed smooth and shiny atrophic patches without any signs of inflammation in the vertex area of the scalp which is presented in Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. No other area of the body including cutaneous, and mucosal was affected and there was no involvement of the nail. The hair pull test was negative. Laboratory investigations included a complete blood count, thyroid function test, and autoimmune profile which were unremarkable. The differential diagnosis included discoid lupus erythematosus (DLE), lichen planopilaris (LPP), folliculitis decalvans (FD), follicular degeneration syndrome, and Alopecia areata. To reach a definitive diagnosis, a scalp skin biopsy was performed which revealed atrophy of the epidermis and fibrosis in the dermis with little to moderate follicular clogging as shown in Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. The diagnosis of pseudopelade of Brocq was made based on clinical findings and histopathological findings criteria defined by Otto Braun-Falco <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> 1986[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] summarized in Tables <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. We started topical corticosteroids (Class 3) two finger-tip units (0.5&#x000a0;g) and tacrolimus ointment (0.1%) twice a day. The disease progression halted after 3&#x000a0;months.<fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Wide irregular, scarring alopecia on the vertex of the scalp.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-380-g001" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Microscopic image of scalp lesion of vertex showing moderate follicular clogging and absence of sebaceous glands in the dermis without any lymphocytic infiltration.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-380-g002" position="float"/></fig>
<table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Otto Braun-Falco <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> 1986, clinical criteria to diagnose Pseudopelade of Brocq.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical criteria</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female:male&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3:1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate atrophy (later stage)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow progression with spontaneous termination possible</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long course (at least&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;2&#x000a0;years)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild perifollicular erythema (early stage)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Irregular defined and confluent patches of alopecia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DIF&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Negative or at least only IgM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Otto Braun-Falco <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> 1986, histological criteria to diagnose Pseudopelade of Brocq.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological criteria</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fibrotic streams into subcutis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absence of widespread scarring</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absence of significant follicular plugging</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presence of normal epidermis (only occasionally atrophy)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absence or at least decrease of sabecous glands</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absence of marked inflammation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The first report of the medical condition was made in 1885 in Paris by Brocq. Pseudopelade, named after the French word &#x0201c;pelade,&#x0201d; which refers to alopecia areata[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], is similar to alopecia areata clinically but differs in that it lacks follicular openings, which causes chronic patchy baldness. Primary pseudopelade is typified by an immune-mediated mechanism in which damage to stem cells in the isthmus (bulge area) is caused by perifollicular lymphocytic infiltrates, resulting in permanent hair loss. Idiopathic instances account for about 10% of cases, and few people have a hereditary propensity. &#x0201c;Secondary pseudopelade&#x0201d; describes the last phases of scarring alopecias, including morphea, DLE, FD, and LPP[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>The cause of this condition has yet to be established. Pincelli <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> provide an immunological explanation. Brocq&#x02019;s childhood pseudopelade is uncommon, and this may be the first reported case in two if not three, family members. This shows that our patients have a separate cause, which may involve genetic variables. However, our patients did not show the normal HLA B8/DR3/DR4 pattern that is commonly associated with autoimmune disorders. A family history of autoimmune disease is not typically associated with this syndrome, and environmental variables cannot be ruled out[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>A sparse or moderate lymphocytic Infiltrate around the infundibulum and the absence of sebaceous glands are pathologic hallmarks of an early PPB lesion. In later lesions, the follicular epithelium becomes more and more atrophic and follicles are often surrounded by concentric lamellar fibroplasia until finally the follicle is replaced by fibrous tracts. Unlike in DLE and LPP, the elastic fiber network is preserved and elastin stain might show markedly thickened elastic fibers[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>Pseudopelade of Brocq is considered end-stage permanent alopecia leading to baldness in a few years. The pathogenesis of cicatricial alopecia includes the destruction of hair follicles and subsequent fibrosis. This can be due to damage to the hair follicle itself or damage to the reticular dermis which ultimately damages hair follicles. Stem cells are present in the hair follicle bulge which contributes to the regeneration of hair, loss of these cells results in lasting scarring alopecia<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup>. Pathophysiology is yet to be understood completely and is subject to further research on the topic. No standard treatment for PPB is present. Treatment is usually resistant to topical corticosteroids, 5% minoxidil, and intradermal steroids. Oral steroids are ineffective. If the disease is stable for at least 2&#x000a0;years, surgical options may be considered. It can include scalp reduction surgery or hair transplantation (autologous)<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup>. The pseudopelade of Brocq is insidious in onset, and slow in progression. The diagnosis is based on exclusion without any permanent cure[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>Our case study sheds light on the rare presentation of Pseudopelade of Brocq in adult male patients. It is vital to recognize its limitations as our research is observational and cannot demonstrate the pathogenesis of the disease. Pseudopelade of Brocq which is common in females but rare in male patients, serves as a starting point for additional inquiry regarding causal link and epidemiology of disease.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our patient presented with slowly progressive irregular patches of atrophy in the vertex area of the scalp. There was no evidence of any other systemic and cutaneous illnesses that established the diagnosis of idiopathic PPB. To reduce the progression of disease proper evaluation through examination and biopsy should be done. The disease is treatable with steroids and the patient should be followed along the course of the disease.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal"><p>Published online 9 January 2025</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Patients&#x02019; perspective</title><p>According to the patient, her disease progression decreased after topical corticosteroids and tacrolimus ointment use including progressive hair loss affecting the vertex of the scalp and shiny atrophic patches. She was satisfied with the care provided to her.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>Ethics approval was not required for this case report.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent</title><p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal on request.</p></sec><sec><title>Sources of funding</title><p>The authors received no extramural funding for the study.</p></sec><sec><title>Author&#x02019;s contribution</title><p>The conceptualization was done by M.H.G. and A.W. The literature and drafting of the manuscript were conducted by F.A., R.A., and M.U.B.S. The editing and supervision were performed by A.B.W. All authors have read and agreed to the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest disclosure</title><p>The authors declare no potential conflicts of interest concerning the research, authorship, or publication of this article.</p></sec><sec><title>Research registration unique identifying number (UIN)</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Guarantor</title><p>Abdul Baseer Wardak.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The authors declared the data availability statement.</p></sec><sec><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p>Not commissioned, externally peer-reviewed.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alzolibani</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Otberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pseudopelade of Brocq</article-title>. <source>Dermatol Ther</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18715295</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diwan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gohil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Primary idiopathic pseudopelade of Brocq: five case reports</article-title>. <source>Int J Trichology</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25114452</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohrabi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maria</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The SCARE 2023 guideline: updating consensus surgical case report (SCARE) guidelines</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg Lond Engl</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>1136</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braun-Falco</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmoeckel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pseudopelade of Brocq</article-title>. <source>Dermatologica</source>
<year>1986</year>;<volume>172</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3956816</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Familial incidence of pseudopelade of Brocq</article-title>. <source>Indian J Dermatol Venereol Leprol</source>
<year>1993</year>; <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singhal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pariath</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Primary idiopathic pseudopelade of Brocq in a young child</article-title>. <source>Int J Trichology</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28932062</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>James</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pseudopelade of Brocq occurring in two brothers in childhood</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Dermatol</source>
<year>1994</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8313641</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Update on primary cicatricial alopecias</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15965418</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sellheyer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergfeld</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Histopathologic evaluation of alopecias</article-title>. <source>Am J Dermatol</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>236</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mcelwee</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnosis and management of primary cicatricial alopecia: part I</article-title>. <source>SKINmed</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18174797</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>