<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MS9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Medicine and Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2049-0801</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40109650</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11918787</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AMSU-D-24-01701</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MS9.0000000000002826</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00024</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Experimental Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Extensive surveillance of mosquitoes and molecular investigation of arboviruses in Central Iran</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abedi-Astaneh</surname><given-names>Fatemeh</given-names></name><email>fatemehabediastaneh@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>Hedaiatollah R.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>hedaiatollahraoofirad@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Izanlou</surname><given-names>Hassan</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>Hizan52@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hosseinalipour</surname><given-names>Seied A.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>Abbad-hosseinalipour@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamta</surname><given-names>Amir</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>Hamta.amir@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eshaghieh</surname><given-names>Mohammad</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>M3918134@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>Mahdi</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>Mahdiebrahimi687@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ansari-Cheshmeh</surname><given-names>Mohammad A.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>Ansari9531@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pouriayevali</surname><given-names>Mohammad H.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>MHPouriayevali@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salehi-Vaziri</surname><given-names>Mostafa</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>Mostafavaziri1985@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jalali</surname><given-names>Tahmineh</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>jalalitahmineh@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Talbalaghi</surname><given-names>Asghar</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>talbalaghi@libero.it</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>Ebrahim</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>abbasie.ebrahim@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Research Centre for Environmental Pollutions, Deputy for Health, Qom University of Medical Sciences, Qom, Iran</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Biology and Control of Disease Vectors, School of Health, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Arboviruses and Viral Hemorrhagic Fevers (National Reference Laboratory), Pasteur Institute of Iran, Tehran, Iran</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Faculty of Public Health, Department of Biology and Vector Control, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Zand Street, JGHF+XFG, P.O. Box No. 3761833650, Shiraz, Fars Province, Iran. Tel.: +98 9124338389. E-mail: <email>abbasie.ebrahim@gmail.com</email> (E. Abbasi).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>87</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0</ext-link> (CCBY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ms9-87-130.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Arboviruses are one of the greatest threats to animal and public health. <italic toggle="yes">Culicidae</italic> family is one of the most important vectors for the transmission of arboviruses in the world. According to the geographical, demographic, and climatic features of Qom city in Iran, it can be a suitable region for vectors and therefore transmission of arboviruses.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>In this study, which was conducted between 2019 and 2020 in different parts of Qom city, 83&#x000a0;414 mosquitoes were collected, and after evaluating the species of mosquitoes based on morphological and molecular detection, the presence of alphaviruses, flaviviruses, and phleboviruses were evaluated using genus-specific Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) assays.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>In this study, <italic toggle="yes">Culex tarsalis, Culex theileri, and Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> were detected, including the first recorded presence of <italic toggle="yes">Culex tarsalis</italic> in Iran. No infections with alphavirus, flavivirus, or phlebovirus were identified in the collected mosquitoes.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Climatic and weather changes are the basis for the growth and spread of vectors and, consequently, the spread of arboviral diseases, and this issue seems to be very important to the necessity of increasing and continuing entomological and virological studies.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>arboviruses</kwd><kwd>Culicidae</kwd><kwd>entomological surveillance</kwd><kwd>Iran</kwd><kwd>PCR</kwd><kwd>vector</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Arthropod-borne viruses circulate between vertebrate hosts and arthropod vectors. Arboviruses has been considered a serious public health challenge as they make up more than 17% of infections and have affected the lives of millions of people in a wide geographical area around the world<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup>. It is estimated that more than 520 viruses are transmitted by mosquitoes of which 130 are medically important<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup>. The most important arboviruses mainly belong to the families of <italic toggle="yes">Togaviridae</italic> (genus Alphavirus), <italic toggle="yes">Flaviridae</italic> (genus Flavivirus), Orthobunyavirus, and Phlebovirus<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup>. Mosquitoes such as <italic toggle="yes">Culicidae</italic> family are well-known vectors for arboviruses worldwide<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup>. There are 3100 species, 34 genera, and three subfamilies in the <italic toggle="yes">Culicidae</italic> family; The genuses/genera of the two subfamilies Anophelinae (<italic toggle="yes">Anopheles</italic>) and Culicinae (<italic toggle="yes">Aedes, Culex, Culiseta, Mansonia, Hemagogus, Sabethes,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">psoraphora</italic>), are the most important vectors of arboviruses<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>In recent years, the risk of spreading mosquito vectors of arboviruses has increased significantly due to climate change and globalization, so that in the last decade, the world has seen widespread outbreaks and epidemics of these viruses, such as chikungunya, West Nile, Zika, and dengue viruses<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup>. Apart from Went Nile virus, there have been no reports of autochthonous transmission of Zika, dengue, and chikungunya viruses<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup>. However, imported cases of chikungunya and dengue viruses have been documented from endemic countries mostly in East Asia<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>The study addresses the presence of <italic toggle="yes">Culex tarsalis</italic> in Iran, linking it to similar research in Southern Europe and the Middle East, where climatic conditions foster mosquito breeding and arbovirus transmission. It highlights the shared Mediterranean climate of countries like Spain and Italy, where <italic toggle="yes">C. tarsalis</italic> is associated with West Nile virus outbreaks. The findings emphasize the need for expanded surveillance in Iran and neighboring regions, noting that changing climates and human activities might encourage the spread of this species. The study enriches existing knowledge by documenting a previously unreported mosquito species in Iran and underscores the importance of monitoring emerging vectors in light of global climate change and urbanization, which may elevate arbovirus transmission risks<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Owing to the fact that there is a close association between arboviruses and their mosquito vectors, the geographical distribution of vectors can be used to estimate the risk of emergence of arboviral infections and their outbreaks<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup>. Although several studies investigated the mosquitoes&#x02019; fauna in Iran<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>-<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup>, there is no information regarding the arboviruses&#x02019; vectors fauna in Qom, Central Iran. The Qom is the main crossroad of Iran for the transportation of goods and passengers of Iran. Qom is the pole of Shiism in the world; it has holy places such as the holy shrine of Bibi Fatima Masoumeh, the holy mosque of Jamkaran; and the diversity of the presence of immigrants and pilgrims with ethnicities from most parts of Iran and nationalists from more than 100 countries. This city is the transportation crossroad of the country, so it is very important to control infectious diseases, carriers, and disease reservoirs.</p><p>Since some Aedes species are highly adaptable to various climatic, geographical, and nutritional conditions, they have successfully spread across tropical, subtropical, and temperate regions. Additionally, as urban insects, they are often transported by human vehicles. Notably, vehicles carrying pilgrims and travelers from Iran&#x02019;s southeastern neighboring countries sometimes pass-through border provinces before reaching Qom, while others arrive directly from these countries. Therefore, it is possible to transfer Aedes mosquitoes of these vehicles to the city of Qom&#x02014;the place of residence for a few days of the these people. The risk of spreading mosquito vectors of arboviruses has increased significantly due to climate change and globalization, so that in the last decade, the world has seen widespread outbreaks and epidemics of these viruses, such as dengue, Zika, chikungunya, and West Nile viruses. Because the exact identification of mosquitoes is essential for controlling the species that are vectors of human and animal diseases<sup>[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup>. Therefore, this study was designed to discover the circulating mosquitoes in Qom province and investigate the alphaviruses, flaviviruses, and phleboviruses infections in them.</p><p>The detection of <italic toggle="yes">C. tarsalis</italic> in Iran, despite the absence of arboviruses in this study, is significant for public health planning and vector control efforts. This species, which could become a vector for viruses like West Nile, poses a potential future disease risk as environmental conditions change. Early identification of <italic toggle="yes">C. tarsalis</italic> allows for proactive surveillance and control strategies to prevent disease outbreaks. Additionally, as Iran borders countries with prevalent arboviruses, awareness of cross-border transmission risks is crucial. The study underscores the importance of enhancing vector surveillance and management in response to emerging mosquito species<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>-<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>We will address this by discussing possible reasons for negative arbovirus findings, including seasonal timing, assay sensitivity, and low prevalence of arboviruses in the region. These factors likely contributed to the lack of detected viruses, despite thorough surveillance. This discussion will highlight the importance of continuous monitoring to record any seasonal or sporadic changes in arbovirus circulation.</p><p>Arbovirus surveillance is increasingly important for public health, as climate change and urbanization expand the range of vector-borne diseases like West Nile virus, dengue, chikungunya, and Zika. Studies from regions such as Southern Europe and the Middle East underscore the need for enhanced monitoring systems in Iran. The detection of <italic toggle="yes">Culex</italic> species in Iran parallels findings from Europe, highlighting similar risks. Advances in molecular techniques, particularly real-time PCR, have improved virus detection, supporting the choice of methodologies in surveillance research. Comparisons with similar ecological regions can contextualize the study&#x02019;s findings and address the influence of mosquito species diversity on arbovirus transmission. Additionally, citing regional studies justifies the necessity for surveillance in Iran, reflecting broader trends in neighboring countries.</p><p>The manuscript addresses critical gaps in arbovirus surveillance in the Middle East and North Africa, stressing the importance of the current research. The manuscript is encouraged to propose future research directions, such as expanding surveillance and using climate models for vector population predictions.</p><p>The detection of <italic toggle="yes">C. tarsalis</italic> in Iran carries significant implications for public health, particularly concerning the potential transmission of arboviruses like West Nile virus and other pathogens. This finding underscores the necessity for enhanced surveillance and vector control measures in response to the evolving landscape of mosquito-borne diseases. Additionally, the identification of new mosquito species emphasizes the importance of research and collaboration in understanding vector ecology and mitigating public health risks.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Study area</title><p>The Qom province in Iran (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) is located in the center of the country with an altitude of 900 m above sea level. The population is approximately 1&#x000a0;365&#x000a0;000, and different types of climatic conditions are seen such as the mountainous in the western and southern parts, semi-desert in the central part, and hot and dry desert in the Eastern regions. The warmest months are June and July, while January is the coldest month.<fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Qom province in Iran, the study map.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-130-g001" position="float"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec><title>Collection of Culicidae mosquitoes</title><p>Eight traps (four Biogents (BG) traps and four CO<sub>2</sub> traps) were used to catch adult mosquitoes (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Five separate ecological zones were identified for the field placement of eight traps in the Qom province. The traps were placed at the entrances of the city of Qom, from the north, northwest, southeast, and southwest of the country. One CO<sub>2</sub> trap and one BG trap were placed in the Mehr-o-Mah rest area and tourist complex, one CO<sub>2</sub> trap was placed in the Qom-Tehran toll plaza, one CO<sub>2</sub> trap and one BG trap were placed in the 72 Tan Park, one BG trap was placed in the Maral Setareh tourist complex, and one CO<sub>2</sub> trap and one BG trap were placed in the Alavi Garden (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">Left</italic>: Biogents (BG) trap and <italic toggle="yes">Right</italic>: CO<sub>2</sub> trap.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-130-g002" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Map of the study area, Qom city, Qom province, Iran, 2018.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-130-g003" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>Mosquitoes contribute significantly to local ecosystems, serving as food sources for predators and as pollinators, indicating ecological health. This study identified 11 mosquito species, with their diversity reflecting a balanced ecosystem. As environmental indicators, certain species can signal habitat quality changes, while the presence of diverse species suggests potential risks for disease transmission, even when not directly linked to outbreaks. Key species like <italic toggle="yes">C. tarsalis</italic> are known vectors for West Nile virus, while <italic toggle="yes">Aedes</italic> species may carry other arboviruses. Competition for resources among species can influence population dynamics and disease risk, highlighting the necessity for ongoing monitoring to understand shifts in transmission patterns due to ecological changes.</p><p>The diversity of 11 mosquito species in a study raises important questions about vector competence related to virus transmission. Different species may serve varying roles as primary, secondary, or incidental vectors, increasing co-infection risks and complicating disease dynamics. This highlights the necessity for targeted vector control strategies tailored to the ecological and behavioral characteristics of each species, as well as the implementation of integrated vector management approaches. Effective control measures should include habitat reduction, insecticide use, and public education. Additionally, comprehensive mosquito monitoring programs are essential for tracking population changes and mitigating arbovirus outbreak risks in response to environmental factors. The study emphasizes the ecological importance of mosquito diversity and the need for ongoing surveillance and targeted strategies.</p><p>The BG traps were installed before sunrise. The CO<sub>2</sub> traps were installed at dusk and dismounted half an hour after sunrise of the following day. In CO<sub>2</sub> traps, light was used as an additional adult mosquito&#x02019;s attractant. Traps were installed in public places, such as parks and tourist complexes. The <italic toggle="yes">Culicidae</italic> mosquitoes were morphologically identified within 1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;h, and some of them were selected as pool and kept at liquid nitrogen for further investigation for species of mosquitoes and possible presence of arboviral infection.</p></sec><sec><title>Morphological identification of mosquitoes</title><p>Collected mosquitoes were transferred to the entomology laboratory and placed in dry ice for a few minutes, and microscopic diagnosis was done within 1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;h, as previously described<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup>. In microscopic diagnosis, diagnostic keys and a 60&#x000d7; stereomicroscope lens were used. Undetectable or suspected mosquitoes and a number of identified mosquitoes were selected for molecular testing. Each pool contained an average of 40 mosquitoes of one species; of some species, only one mosquito was caught.</p></sec><sec><title>Molecular identification of mosquitoes</title><p>A total of 20 pools of mosquitoes were subjected to molecular identification and morphological identification. These 20 pools were selected randomly and sent to the Department of Arboviruses and Viral Hemorrhagic Fevers (National Ref Lab), Pasteur Institute of Iran, while maintaining the cold chain using dry ice and a cold box for molecular investigations. All samples were stored at &#x02212;70&#x000b0;C immediately after receiving for further analyses.</p><p>The rationale for selecting only 20 pools can be further expanded. Although logistical limitations impacted the sample size, we strategically selected pools to cover diverse species and geographic zones, thereby maximizing representativeness across the mosquito population in Qom. This selection aimed to ensure that the chosen pools accurately reflected the ecological and virological characteristics of the entire sample.</p><p>The selection of 20 pools for molecular analysis was driven by logistical constraints, resource availability, and the need for scientific rigor. Molecular analysis requires specialized resources and is time-consuming, making it impractical to test all samples. To ensure validity, the pools were randomly selected to represent the diversity and geographic range of mosquito populations. This strategy included a variety of species from different ecological settings, covering urban and rural areas, which enhances the reliability of the findings regarding arbovirus transmission risk. Despite the limited sample size, the approach aimed to provide a comprehensive assessment of the broader mosquito population.</p><p>Mosquito samples were preserved at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C for RNA integrity before extraction for molecular analyses targeting arboviruses, particularly West Nile virus. Total RNA was reverse transcribed into cDNA using a high-fidelity enzyme, followed by amplification of specific arboviral genes through Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR). Challenges included RNA degradation, which was mitigated by using RNase-free reagents and controlled conditions; however, some degradation impacted cDNA quality. Sensitivity issues were addressed by including control samples, and PCR conditions were optimized to enhance specificity. Future research could utilize multiplex PCR and advanced techniques like quantitative PCR and next-generation sequencing for improved detection and understanding of arboviruses.</p><p>Future research should prioritize the screening of arboviruses with significant public health implications, specifically West Nile virus, St. Louis Encephalitis virus, chikungunya virus, dengue virus, and Zika virus. Surveillance for these viruses is critical due to their potential for outbreaks and associated health risks. Integration of climate models is also important to predict changes in mosquito distribution and transmission dynamics as influenced by climate change. Collaborative efforts among neighboring countries, including establishing surveillance networks and standardized protocols, are essential for improving detection and response to arboviral threats.</p><p>For molecular characterization of mosquitoes, PCR amplification and sequence analysis of 735 base pair fragments, including mitochondrial COI gene was carried out using SP ID F/SP ID R primers<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup>. Additionally, the specific primers for actin-1 (ActF and R)<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup> were used. Briefly, mosquitoes were homogenized using Tissuelyser II (Qiagen, Germany). The genomic DNA was extracted from pools using a High Pure Viral Nucleic Acid Kit (Roche, Germany) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. PCR was performed by the Hot StarTaq Master Mix Kit (Qiagen, Germany).</p><p>The final volume was 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L for each reaction, performing one cycle at 95&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min, five cycles at 94&#x000b0;C for 40&#x000a0;s, 45&#x000b0;C for 60&#x000a0;s, and 72&#x000b0;C for 60&#x000a0;s, and 35 cycles at 94&#x000b0;C for 40&#x000a0;s, 51&#x000b0;C for 60&#x000a0;s, and 72&#x000b0;C for 60&#x000a0;s, and a final extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 10&#x000a0;min. PCR products (735bp for SP ID primers and 350bp for ACT primers) were sequenced bidirectional using applied biosystem 3130 Genetic Analyzer (Thermofisher, USA). The sequencing raw data were analyzed by CLC Main Workbench software (CLC bio, Denmark) and using BLAST (<ext-link xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi" ext-link-type="uri">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>) for confirmation, then all sequences data were submitted to GenBank (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank</ext-link>) database (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Evaluation of mosquito detection by microscopic method and confirmation by Sanger sequencing</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possible microscopic detection of species</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The list of mosquitoes after sequencing and blasting</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession number</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex pipiens</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex pipiens</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM714817</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex pipiens</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex pipiens</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM628998</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Culex</italic></bold> spp.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Culex tarsalis</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ON420215</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incompatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex theileri</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex theiler</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM638648</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex modestus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex modestus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM638670</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex subochrea</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex subochrea</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not sequenced</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex perexiguus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex perexiguus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not sequenced</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Anopheles</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Anopheles claviger</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM638671</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Aedes caspius</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ochlerotatus caspius</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM638672</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Aedes caspius</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ochlerotatus caspius</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM638673</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Aedes caspius</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ochlerotatus caspius</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM638674</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Aedes caspius</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ochlerotatus caspius</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not sequenced</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex</italic> spp.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex theilerivoucher</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM638676</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incompatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culiseta longiareolata</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culiseta longiareolata</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM638715</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM638717</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex</italic> spp.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM714908</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incompatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM714856</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM714858</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM714899</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compatible</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not sequenced</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Bold entries indicate discrepancies in species identification between morphological examination and molecular sequencing.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec><title>Detection of arboviruses</title><p>Homogenized mosquitoes were used for total RNA extraction using High pure viral RNA kit (Roche, Germany). The presence of Alphaviruses, Flaviviruses, and Phleboviruses RNAs was investigated by Pan Phlebo RT-PCR using ppLF/ppL1R/ppL2R primes, Pan Flavi RT-PCR using MAMD/cFD2 primers, and Pan Alpha RT-PCR using E1-S/E1-C primers<sup>[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup>. All RT-PCR reactions were done using Onestep RT-PCR kit (Qiagen, Germany). The final volume for each reaction was 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L performing one cycle at 50&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;min, 95&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min, 40 cycles at 94&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s, 53&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s, and 72&#x000b0;C for 45&#x000a0;s, and a final extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>In this study, during 2019&#x02013;2020, a total of 83&#x000a0;414 mosquitoes were caught. According to the morphological key, all categorized as <italic toggle="yes">Culicidae</italic> addition 933 Sandfly were caught. Of which, 27,057 <italic toggle="yes">Culicidae</italic> and 116 Sandfly were selected and kept at liquid nitrogen in 367 Pool including 355 <italic toggle="yes">Culicidae</italic> mosquitoes, and 12 were <italic toggle="yes">phlebotomine</italic>. Since the microscopic and molecular diagnoses of <italic toggle="yes">phlebotomine</italic> were the same and no arboviruses were discovered in them, in this article, we will not continue the discussion about phlebotomines and <italic toggle="yes">Culicidae</italic>, each pool contained an average of 76 mosquitoes of one species. To evaluate the results of morphological identification, 20 pools were subjected to morphological identification, as well.</p><p>The results of morphological and molecular characterization of mosquitoes were incompatible for three pools (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Pools no. 3, no. 13, no. 16 were categorized as just <italic toggle="yes">Culex</italic> because their species could not be recognized. In morphological identification, the pool no. 3 was characterized as <italic toggle="yes">C. tarsalis</italic> after genomic analysis. According to the molecular assay, the pool no. 13 was <italic toggle="yes">Culex theilerivoucher</italic>, and the pool no.16 was categorized as <italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> in the molecular assay.</p><p>The negative findings regarding arboviruses should be interpreted as a valuable part of understanding the local vector ecology and public health risks. These results underscore the importance of sustained, comprehensive surveillance to detect future changes in virus circulation. By addressing potential reasons for the negative results&#x02014;such as seasonal factors, assay sensitivity, and low virus circulation&#x02014;the study provides a strong foundation for improving future surveillance and vector control programs in the region.</p><p>In comparison, in the microscopic method, of these 20 Pools, three were misdiagnosed or incorrect. <italic toggle="yes">C. tarsalis</italic> has been reported for the first time in Iran, and the main reason for the lack of detection by the entomologist was the absence of this mosquito in the available diagnostic keys in Iran. Therefore, the entomologist could only determine the genus (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">Culex theileri</italic> has a bright transverse band on the abdomen<sup>[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</sup>, but in our study, it was a rectangular band in the third abdominal band (Figs. <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). No Alphavirus, Flavivirus, or Phlebovirus infection was identified in the collected mosquitoes.<fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">Culex tarsalis. Cx. tarsalis</italic> was not included in the diagnostic keys of Iran. The genus was identified by the entomologist, while species identification was confirmed by the national reference laboratory.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-130-g004" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">Cx. theileri</italic> (unknown to Entomologist).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-130-g005" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p><italic toggle="yes">C. theileri</italic> has a bright transverse band on the abdomen. There is a rectangular band in the third abdominal band. Of course, it has the vertex of a bright triangle (Fig. <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).<fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">Cx. theileri</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-130-g006" position="float"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Considering that Qom province is a central city for the transit of goods to the south and north of Iran, mosquitoes can be moved mechanically into or out of this region. In addition, a large number of tourists from Iran or other Muslim countries travel to this city for religious purposes and can be bitten by mosquitoes during those periods of residency.</p><p>In our study, 11 species were collected and identified, which included <italic toggle="yes">C. quinquefasciatus, Culex pipiens, C. theileri, Culex subochrea, Aedes (Ochlerotatus) caspius, Culex modestus, C. theileri voucher, Anopheles claviger, Culex perexiguus, Culiseta longiareolata,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C. tarsalis</italic> in Qom province. <italic toggle="yes">C. tarsalis</italic> was identified for the first time from Iran. Asgarian <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. in fauna and larval habitat, from April to December 2019, identified three genera <italic toggle="yes">Anopheles, Culiseta</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Culex</italic> in Kashan and also <italic toggle="yes">Culex pipiens</italic> (37.36%) and <italic toggle="yes">Cx. Theileri</italic> (26.10%) had the highest abundance of species<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup>. Nikookar <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. reported that <italic toggle="yes">C. pipiens</italic> as the most abundant species in fauna and larval habitat in Neka County, Northern Iran<sup>[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Moradi-asl <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. identified 13 species of mosquitoes in the form of four genera (Anopheles, Aedes, Culex, and Culiseta) in the north-western province of Iran, and in this study, the Culex and <italic toggle="yes">Culex pipiens</italic> were the most abundant genus and species, respectively<sup>[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>In the current study, the most identified species is <italic toggle="yes">C. quinquefasciatus</italic>, but Saghafipour <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. in Qom province reported four genera among Diptera: <italic toggle="yes">Culicidae</italic>, which included 14 species, and from them, <italic toggle="yes">anopheles claviger</italic> was the most common species<sup>[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</sup>. Therefore, it seems that the identification of different rates among the species can be due to different conditions and climatic variables. On the other hand, morphological studies alone are not sufficient to differentiate species, and molecular methods can be helpful in identifying the species with high sensitivity. <italic toggle="yes">C. tarsalis</italic> are strong flyers, covering distances of up to 4 km for a blood meal and feeds from birds, cattle, horses, and human<sup>[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Finding a new species of mosquito for the first time in Iran also warns that we must always wait for new species of mosquitoes, their establishment, and the potential spread of emerging and re-emerging diseases. In addition, because of the genetic and behavioral changes in each species, physical diagnosis becomes more difficult, and therefore molecular detection should always be used besides physical and morphological diagnosis.</p><p>Except for some molecular and serological reports for West Nile virus in Iran, chikungunya virus and dengue viruses have been reported as imported cases into Iran. In the present study, no Alphavirus, Flavivirus, and Phlebovirus have been reported<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>-<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>However, due to climate change, there is a possibility that these viruses will spread in the future. Therefore, continuous entomological and virological studies, along with field studies on vectors in the region, seem to be necessary.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The weather and climate changes that have occurred in Iran have caused the appearance of new species and even changes in the lifestyle of mosquitoes. Therefore, continuous studies in different geographical areas on viral vectors provide new information about the spread of arboviral diseases and their vectors.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank the managers and personnel of the Qom Health Deputy, Qom University of Medical Sciences, the Department of Arboviruses and Viral Hemorrhagic Fevers at the Pasteur Institute of Iran, as well as the municipalities of Qom, Qom Green Space Organization, and the General Directorate of Cultural Heritage, Handicrafts, and Tourism of Qom.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal"><p>Published online 9 January 2025</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Ethical considerations approval</title><p>This project was submitted in to the Qom University of Medical Sciences with code number 97959.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Sources of funding</title><p>The authors would like to thank all the managers and personnel of the Qom University of Medical Sciences.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contribution</title><p>All authors contributed equally to this study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest disclosure</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Research registration unique identifying number (UIN)</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Guarantor</title><p>Ebrahim Abbasi.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>All study data are included in the text of the article and available.</p></sec><sec><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p>Not commissioned, externally peer-reviewed.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kading</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brault</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beckham</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Global perspectives on arbovirus outbreaks: a 2020 snapshot</article-title>. <source>Trop Med Infect Dis</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>142</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32906771</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jupp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <part-title>Chikungunya virus disease</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>C M</surname><given-names>Okeoma</given-names></name></person-group>
<edition>(Ed.)</edition>, <source>The Arboviruses</source>. <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>: <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcondes</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Generalities and Importance of Arthropod-borne Diseases</source>. <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mannasse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mendelson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orshan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Usutu virus RNA in mosquitoes, Israel, 2014&#x02013;2015</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1699</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28930008</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talavera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birnberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nu&#x000f1;ez</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Culex flavivirus infection in a <italic toggle="yes">Culex pipiens</italic> mosquito colony and its effects on vector competence for Rift Valley fever phlebovirus</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29291748</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abedi-Astaneh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akhavan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shirzadi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Species diversity of sand flies and ecological niche model of <italic toggle="yes">Phlebotomus papatasi</italic> in central Iran</article-title>. <source>Acta Trop</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>149</volume>:<fpage>246</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26071647</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Durden</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Medical and Veterinary Entomology</source>. <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Musso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodriguez-Morales</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Unexpected outbreaks of arbovirus infections: lessons learned from the Pacific and tropical America</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>e355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e361</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29934112</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah-Hosseini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chinikar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ataei</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of West Nile virus genome, Iran</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1419</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25061976</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pouriayevali</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jalali</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Imported cases of chikungunya virus in Iran</article-title>. <source>BMC Infect Dis</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30606108</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salehi-Vaziri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fazlalipour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baniasadi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Solving the mystery of dengue in Iran; are we close to an answer?</article-title>
<source>Iran J Virol</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chianese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stelitano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Astorri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>West Nile virus: an overview of current information</article-title>. <source>Transl Med Rep</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>8145</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Candeloro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ippoliti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Spatio-temporal identification of areas suitable for West Nile disease in the Mediterranean Basin and Central Europe</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0146024</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26717483</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amoa-Bosompem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murota</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Entomological assessment of the status and risk of mosquito-borne arboviral transmission in Ghana</article-title>. <source>Viruses</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32012771</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asgarian</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moosa-Kazemi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sedaghat</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fauna and larval habitat characteristics of mosquitoes (Diptera: Culicidae) in Kashan County, Central Iran, 2019</article-title>. <source>J Arthropod Borne Dis</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34277857</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moosa-Kazemi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Etemadi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sedaghat</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Investigation on mosquitoes fauna (Diptera: Culicidae) and probable vector of West Nile Virus in Lorestan province, Western Iran</article-title>. <source>J Arthropod Borne Dis</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>397</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36644308</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paksa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sedaghat</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vatandoost</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Biodiversity of mosquitoes (Diptera: Culicidae) with emphasis on potential arbovirus vectors in East Azerbaijan province, northwestern Iran</article-title>. <source>J Arthropod Borne Dis</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31346536</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>ATalbalaghi</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular approach for identification of mosquito species (Diptera: Culicidae) in Province of Alessandria, Piedmont, Italy</article-title>. <source>Eur J Entomol</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daliri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Knockdown resistance (kdr) associated organochlorine resistance in mosquito-borne diseases (<italic toggle="yes">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>): systematic study of reviews and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>e0011991</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39159258</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="paper"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daliri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Talbalaghi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Knockdown resistance (kdr) associated organochlorine resistance in mosquito-borne diseases (<italic toggle="yes">Culex pipiens</italic>): systematic study of reviews and meta-analysis</article-title>, <source>medRxiv</source> (<year>2023</year>) <comment>2023.12. 17.23300098</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="paper"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moemenbellah-Fard</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of chikungunya, dengue, and West Nile arboviruses in Iran based on enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA): a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <comment>medRxiv</comment> (<year>2024</year>) <comment>2024.09. 12.24313525</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moosa-Kazemi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>H</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nikookar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Culicinae (Diptera: Culicidae) mosquitoes in Chabahar county, Sistan and Baluchistan province, southeastern Iran</article-title>. <source>Iran J Arthropod Borne Dis</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22808369</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samanidou-Voyadjoglou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harbach</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Keys to the adult female mosquitoes (Culicidae) of Greece</article-title>. <source>European Mosquito Bulletin</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>L-P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hapuarachchi</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>DNA barcoding: complementing morphological identification of mosquito species in Singapore</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24411014</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorman</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bartholomay</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Universal primers for the amplification and sequence analysis of actin-1 from diverse mosquito species</article-title>. <source>J Am Mosq Control Assoc</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>214</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20649132</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weisend</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kajihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comprehensive molecular detection of tick-borne phleboviruses leads to the retrospective identification of taxonomically unassigned bunyaviruses and the discovery of a novel member of the genus phlebovirus</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>594</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>604</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25339769</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwashita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Futami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mosquito arbovirus survey in selected areas of Kenya: detection of insect-specific virus</article-title>. <source>Trop Med Health</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29317853</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stojanovich</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mosquitoes of Italy: mosquitoes of the Italian biogeographic area which includes the Republic of Malta, the French Island of Corsica and all of Italy except the Far-Northern provinces</article-title>. <source>Chester J Stojanovich</source>
<year>1997</year>;<volume>200</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nikookar</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moosa-Kazemi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yaghoobi-Ershadi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fauna and larval habitat characteristics of mosquitoes in Neka County, Northern Iran</article-title>. <source>J Arthropod Borne Dis</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26623437</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moradi-Asl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hazrati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vatandoost</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fauna and larval habitat characteristics of mosquitoes (Diptera: Culicidae) in Ardabil province, Northwestern Iran</article-title>. <source>J Health</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saghafipour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abai</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farzinnia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mosquito (Diptera: Culicidae) fauna of Qom province, Iran</article-title>. <source>J Arthropod Borne Dis</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23293779</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="paper"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reisen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bionomics and ecology of <italic toggle="yes">Culex tarsalis</italic> and other potential mosquito vector species</article-title>. <year>1990</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ataie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moosa-Kazemi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vatandoost</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Assessing the susceptibility status of mosquitoes (Diptera: Culicidae) in a dirofilariasis focus, northwestern Iran</article-title>. <source>J Arthropod Borne Dis</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26114140</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baniasadi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salehi-Vaziri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jalali</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An imported case of dengue fever in Iran, 2015</article-title>. <source>Iran J Virol</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalantari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salehi-Vaziri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pouriayevali</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Seroprevalence of West Nile virus in Khuzestan province, southwestern Iran, 2016&#x02013;2017</article-title>. <source>J Vector Borne Dis</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32655076</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>