<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MS9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Medicine and Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2049-0801</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40109619</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11918742</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MS9.0000000000002758</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AMSU-D-24-01912</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00050</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Successful arm replantation using traditional surgical techniques: a case report from a low-resource country</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abubakir</surname><given-names>Malaka</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><email>Malake19.19@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Sabbagh</surname><given-names>Lana</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><email>lanasabbagh88@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>Ghaiyath</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>ghaiyathkhalil@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Al Ali</surname><given-names>Shahama</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><email>ghaiyathkhalil@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tfankji</surname><given-names>Salim</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>stfankji@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alkanj</surname><given-names>Hussein</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>drhkanj@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Faculty of Medicine, University of Aleppo, Aleppo, Syrian Arab Republic</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Vascular Surgery, Aleppo University Hospital, University of Aleppo, Aleppo, Syrian Arab Republic.</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Cardiovascular Surgery, Aleppo University Hospital, University of Aleppo, Aleppo, Syrian Arab Republic</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Faculty of Medicine, University of Aleppo, 205, Az-Zahraa district, Aleppo, Syrian Arab Republic. Tel.: +963 942055685. E-mail: <email>lanasabbagh88@gmail.com</email> (L. Sabbagh).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>87</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0</ext-link> (CCBY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ms9-87-339.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction:</title><p>Upper limb replantation requires rapid intervention by a multidisciplinary team and appropriate equipment to rescue the limb. Note that the success of the operation and the decision to perform it depend on several factors. This case report presents an upper limb replantation performed using traditional surgical techniques.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation:</title><p>A 12-year-old boy presented to our hospital with a crushing injury to the right upper arm, which was amputated at the lower third of the humerus, with the biceps brachii tendon remaining intact. The first aid included resuscitation and intravenous fluid administration to maintain hemodynamic stability. The surgeons replanted the arm by immobilizing the fracture with Kirschner wires, performing several arterial and venous anastomoses, and suturing the damaged nerve and muscle aponeurosis in a 3-h operation. The patient was discharged after 5&#x000a0;days without any complications but was recommended to undergo physical therapy to regain his arm movement and is currently undergoing monthly follow-ups to ensure the required improvement.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion:</title><p>Upper limb replantation is a complicated process that enables the conservation of arm function and appearance. This requires rapid intervention by a multidisciplinary team. Additionally, advanced equipment, such as microsurgical tools, provides greater success and ease of revascularization.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>To successfully re-implant an amputated limb, several factors must be considered: surgeon experience, availability of necessary equipment, and provision of post-operative care. Despite lacking advanced tools, surgeons can rely on their surgical skills to overcome this challenge.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>amputated arm</kwd><kwd>case report</kwd><kwd>replantation</kwd><kwd>traditional techniques</kwd><kwd>upper limb</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Replanting an upper limb is a complex process that requires immediate and rapid intervention from a multidisciplinary team in addition to the availability of appropriate equipment[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The first clinical replantation of a limb was performed by Malt and McKhann in 1962[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Although upper limb amputation is not usually a life-threatening condition, it negatively affects the overall quality of life of patients[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>The main aim of traumatic replantation is to achieve optimal functionality[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This outcome depends on factors within our control, such as the duration of ischemia, as well as those beyond our control, including age, degree of nerve injury, and the level of amputation[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The decision to proceed with limb replantation is based on several factors, including the importance of the organ, level of injury, mechanism of injury, and desired functional outcome[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The success of the operation depends on several factors, such as a short duration of ischemia, proper management of the amputated part, type of cutting tool used, and mechanism of injury[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>Unfortunately, owing to the harsh circumstances resulting from the war, there is a notable absence of advanced equipment and tools. Consequently, surgeons faced a major challenge in saving the limb of a 12-year-old child who was admitted to the hospital after experiencing a crushing injury to the arm, which damaged all structures except the biceps brachii tendon and the surrounding skin. This case report has been reported in line with the Surgical CAse REport &#x0201c;SCARE&#x0201d; 2023 Criteria[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 12-year-old boy presented to the emergency department with a crushing injury caused by a kneading machine. The right upper arm was amputated in the lower third of the humerus, with the biceps brachii tendon remaining intact (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A).<fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>(A) The amputated part upon arrival, the arm was subtotally amputated at the lower third of the humerus, with the biceps brachii tendon remaining intact. (B) Preoperative X-ray.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-339-g001" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>On arrival, the warm ischemia time was 4&#x000a0;h with Glasco coma scale 13. The limb was tied with a cloth to prevent bleeding and presented pallor and coolness. Initial intervention in the emergency room included resuscitating the patient following The Air way, Breathing, Circulation, Disability, Exposure &#x0201c;ABCD&#x0201d; approach and administering fluid replacement with intravenous fluids to maintain hemodynamic stability. An arm X-ray revealed a displaced fracture of the lower humerus with a change in the bone&#x02019;s axis (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). Physical examination revealed material loss in the medial and posterior sections of the lower third of the humerus, along with bone crepitus. The pulse was unpalpable in the brachial artery at the elbow, as well as in the ulnar and radial arteries, with no signal appearing on arterial Doppler ultrasound examination. Moreover, the median nerve was cut, also the ulnar and the radial nerves were transected at the level of the lower humerus. Laboratory tests revealed low hemoglobin levels and a reactive increase in WBCs. The patient&#x02019;s family confirmed that the patient did not have any significant medical or surgical history prior to the operation.</p><p>The surgical team, which consisted of vascular, orthopedic, and neurosurgeons, decided to perform a replantation operation, starting with the administration of general anesthesia and povidone-iodine sterilization. The orthopedic surgeon immobilized the distal humerus fracture using two Kirschner wires. Vascular surgeons found out that the brachial artery was cut with clots inside it, so they isolated the distal and proximal sections of the brachial artery and utilized a Fogarty catheter (2F) to restore blood flow, followed by an end-to-end anastomosis with a (7/0) Prolene suture, ensuring pulse restoration. The basilic vein was isolated in its proximal and distal segments, and an end-to-end anastomosis was performed using a (7/0) Prolene suture. The cephalic vein was also isolated, and its integrity was confirmed to ensure proper venous branch homeostasis (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). The total warm ischemia time was approximately 7&#x000a0;h. The neurosurgeon isolated the proximal and distal segments of the ulnar and radial nerves and then sequentially sutured them using (7/0) Prolene sutures (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). Additionally, the median nerve was isolated in its proximal and distal segments and sutured with (7/0) Prolene sutures as well. Finally, vascular surgeons sutured the muscle aponeurosis and closed the wound using sutures and a sterile dressing. The skin was left to heal by the second intention due to significant skin loss, completing the operation within 3&#x000a0;h (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B and <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C).<fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>(A) The end-to-end anastomosis of the brachial artery, basal vein, and the ulnar nerve. (B) Material loss of skin in the lateral part of the lower arm. (C) The final result after muscles approximation and skin closure, medial part of the lower humerus.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-339-g002" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>During the operation, the patient received a tetanus vaccine along with ceftriaxone 1&#x000a0;g, 2500 IU of heparin as a loading dose and one unit of blood alongside one unit of plasma.</p><p>After the operation, an X-ray was performed to assess the condition of the arm (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B). The prescribed regimen of medications included ceftriaxone following an allergy test and cetamol, flagyl, amikacin, heparin, and saline serum on a daily basis. The initial outcomes of the operation revealed successful revascularization of the limb, as demonstrated by the restoration of normal capillary refill time and the finger oximeter registering an oxygenation rate of 97%. The limb had healthy coloration.<fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>(A) Post-operative anterior X-ray. (B) Post-operative posterior X-ray; showing the internal fixation by k. wires.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-339-g003" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>The patient did not need to stay in the intensive care unit. After a post-operative observation period of 5&#x000a0;days, the patient did not experience any complications such as edema or infection, which allowed for discharge. The patient underwent weekly follow-up visits, and after 3&#x000a0;months, a palpable pulse was observed. Wound rehabilitation demonstrated excellent improvement (Fig. <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A and <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B); however, limb movement remained impaired, with associated paresthesia along the ulnar nerve distribution. The cosmetic appearance was satisfactory with anticipated potential residual scarring. Patient satisfaction was high owing to successful limb preservation.<fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>(A) The arm after 2&#x000a0;weeks at the follow-up. (B) The arm after 3&#x000a0;months at the follow-up.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-339-g004" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>Recommendations for the patient included initiating physical therapy to enhance limb mobility and scheduling an electromyography evaluation after 6&#x000a0;months, with ongoing weekly follow-up.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Upper limb replantation presents a significant challenge for surgeons, primarily aimed at conserving both the function and aesthetics of the arm[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This complex procedure requires a multidisciplinary team that includes vascular, neurological, and orthopedic surgeons[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Patients with traumatic amputation injuries are managed in the emergency department according to the Advanced Trauma Life Support Protocol[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The initial management steps before the replantation procedure involve controlling bleeding, administering intravenous fluids to prevent volume loss, keeping the patient warm to avoid hypothermia, and providing prophylactic tetanus and antibiotics<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup>. The amputated part should be immersed in saline-moistened gauze rather than in water and placed inside a plastic bag. Then, the plastic bag should be placed on ice<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup>. It is crucial to not place the amputated part directly on ice, as this can lead to vasospasm, compromising the residual vascular supply<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup>. Intraoperatively, surgeons should first identify and safeguard the nerves, blood vessels, and tendons; shorten the bone to alleviate tension on the neurovascular bundle; employ K-wire fixation; ensure adequate arterial blood flow; and repair the arteries and veins through anastomosis. If feasible, all tendons should also be repaired[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Post-operatively, anticoagulation therapy is typically recommended[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The patient&#x02019;s room should be kept warm, and the affected limb should be positioned at the heart level to reduce edema without hindering blood flow[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The success of replantation is greatly influenced by the level and mechanism of injury, as well as the surgeon&#x02019;s experience[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Moreover, the Chen classification was developed for the post-operative assessment of upper extremity replantation; this classification is preferred because it effectively evaluates the success of replantation across various levels of amputation[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. It assesses the ability to return to work, perform daily activities, recover sensations, and achieve a range of motion in the affected joint[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Several post-operative complications may arise, including early complications due to infection or microvascular breakdown[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Late complications may include cold intolerance, joint ankylosis, neuropathic pain, tendon adhesions, bone malunion, and nonunion[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Physiotherapy and occupational therapy are crucial in assisting the patient to recover as much function as possible[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Technical advances in microsurgery with modern tools, such as microscopes and microsurgical instruments, have significantly increased the success rate of revascularization after limb amputations<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup>. However, due to the circumstances in Syria and the limited resources available, we had to utilize traditional surgical techniques to repair the affected structures.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>To conclude, upper limb replantation is a serious surgical procedure that requires a multidisciplinary team and a specialized center equipped with essential equipment, such as microscopes and microsurgical instruments. This case describes the successful replantation of an amputated arm in a low-resource country, achieved despite the absence of these essential equipment, a satisfactory result, and saved a child&#x02019;s arm, owing to our team&#x02019;s surgical expertise using traditional surgical techniques. The patient is currently undergoing physical therapy and monthly follow-up to ensure proper functional restoration.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors sincerely thank Dr. Bakri Roumi Jamal for his invaluable assistance in enhancing this manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal"><p>Published online 9 January 2025</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Assistance with the study</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec><title>Presentation</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>Ethical approval was taken from our university.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent</title><p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal upon request.</p></sec><sec><title>Source of funding</title><p>No funding resources.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contribution</title><p>M.A. wrote and critically revised the manuscript. L.S. contributed to writing and critically revising the manuscript. S.A.A. assisted with the manuscript writing. G.K. and S.T. provided case information, participated in the surgery, and followed the patient's treatment. H.A. led the surgery and was responsible for reviewing the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest disclosure</title><p>All authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Research Registration Unique Identifying Number (UIN)</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Guarantor</title><p>Malaka Abubakir and Lana Sabbagh.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The datasets used during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p></sec><sec><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p>Not commissioned, externally peer-reviewed.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brimo Alsaman</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sawas</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al Mohamad</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Successful management of an amputated hand at the distal row level of carpal bones in low-resources country: a case report</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg Case Rep</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>108627</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37574633</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Llagostera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lamas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Role of temporary arterial shunt in the reimplantation of a traumatic above-elbow amputation</article-title>. <source>Vascular</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17573026</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okumu&#x0015f;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>&#x000d6;zkan</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Upper extremity replantation results in our series and review of replantation indications</article-title>. <source>Ulus Travma Ve Acil Cerrahi Derg</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salah</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Replantation of multiple digits and hand amputations: four case reports</article-title>. <source>Cases J</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18577237</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohrabi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maria</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<comment>Collaborators</comment>. <article-title>The SCARE 2023 guideline: updating consensus Surgical Case Report (SCARE) guidelines</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>1136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37013953</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Win</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Management of traumatic amputations of the upper limb</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>348</volume>:<fpage>g255</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24516069</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solarz</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thoder</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Management of major traumatic upper extremity amputations trauma</article-title>. <source>Orthop Clin North Am</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26614927</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yildiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sener</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baki</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Replantation in children</article-title>. <source>Microsurgery</source>
<year>1998</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>410</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9880156</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murrad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rashidi</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altamimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Successfully replanted an amputated hand</article-title>. <source>A Case Report</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iorio</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hand, wrist, forearm, and arm replantation</article-title>. <source>Hand Clin</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30928047</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gulgonen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ozer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term results of major upper extremity replantations</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur Vol</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22045198</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>