<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MS9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Medicine and Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2049-0801</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40109590</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11918737</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MS9.0000000000002846</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AMSU-D-24-01705</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00063</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Use of ultrasonic bone dissector in diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis involving the cervical spine</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scalia</surname><given-names>Gianluca</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>gianluca.scalia@outlook.it</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Giuffrida</surname><given-names>Massimiliano</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>mass.giuffrida@tiscalinet.it</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ponzo</surname><given-names>Giancarlo</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>giancarlo.ponzo@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Furnari</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>massimofurnari@alice.it</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chaurasia</surname><given-names>Bipin</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>trozexa@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref><xref rid="COR0001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Umana</surname><given-names>Giuseppe E.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD, MSc, FACS</degrees><email>umana.nch@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nicoletti</surname><given-names>Giovanni F.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>nicolettigiovanni23@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Neurosurgery Clinic, Department of Head and Neck Surgery, Garibaldi Hospital, Catania, Italy</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Neurosurgery Clinic, Birgunj, Nepal</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Cannizzaro Hospital, Trauma and Gamma Knife Center, Catania, Italy</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>School of Medicine and Surgery, University Kore of Enna, Enna, Italy</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Consultant Neurosurgeon, Neurosurgery Clinic, Birgunj, Nepal. E-mail: <email>trozexa@gmail.com</email> (B. chaurasia).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>87</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives License 4.0</ext-link>, which allows for redistribution, commercial and noncommercial, as long as it is passed along unchanged and in whole, with credit to the author.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ms9-87-398.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction and importance</title><p>Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH), or Forestier&#x02019;s disease, is characterized by ligament and enthesis calcification, mainly in the thoracic spine. Cervical involvement can cause dysphagia due to soft tissue compression, necessitating surgical intervention when conservative measures fail. We assess the efficacy of anterior cervical osteophytectomy with an ultrasonic bone dissector in relieving symptoms and improving outcomes.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 73-year-old male presented with progressive neck pain and dysphagia caused by DISH in the cervical spine. Conservative treatment was ineffective, requiring anterior cervical osteophytectomy using an ultrasonic bone dissector. Postoperative imaging confirmed spinal cord decompression, and the patient experienced significant symptom relief. The ultrasonic bone dissector enabled precise bone resection, facilitating resolution of dysphagia and improving quality of life.</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical discussion</title><p>This case highlights the effectiveness of ultrasonic bone dissection for cervical DISH. The device ensures precise bone removal with minimal soft tissue trauma, reducing complications and promoting recovery. While initial outcomes are promising, long-term studies are needed to compare this method with other interventions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Surgical intervention, particularly anterior cervical osteophytectomy with ultrasonic bone dissection, is effective when conservative treatments fail. Advanced surgical techniques improve patient outcomes and warrant further investigation to establish their role in managing cervical DISH.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cervical spine</kwd><kwd>diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis</kwd><kwd>dysphagia</kwd><kwd>surgical intervention</kwd><kwd>ultrasonic bone dissector</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH), also referred to as Forestier&#x02019;s disease, is a systemic condition of unknown etiology characterized by progressive calcification and ossification of ligaments and entheses<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup>. While DISH most commonly affects the thoracic spine, involvement of the cervical spine can lead to severe clinical manifestations, including spinal cord compression and impingement on adjacent structures, notably presenting with dysphagia and respiratory compromise in advanced cases<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup>. In cases where conservative management fails to alleviate symptoms, surgical intervention becomes essential to restore function and improve quality of life<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup>. Recent advancements in surgical instrumentation have introduced the ultrasonic bone dissector as an innovative tool, enabling precise bone resection while minimizing trauma to adjacent soft tissues. This represents a significant advantage in the complex anatomy of the cervical spine, where precision and soft tissue preservation are critical. This technical case report details the surgical technique and clinical outcomes associated with the use of the ultrasonic bone dissector in treating DISH involving the cervical spine. The report aims to highlight the benefits of this technology, including improved precision, reduced perioperative complications, and enhanced recovery, offering a valuable approach for complex cases of cervical spine DISH.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>We present the case of a 73-year-old male patient who presented with a history of progressive neck pain (Visual Analogue Scale Score of 6/10 and Neck Disability Index of 30%), dysphagia, and difficulty in swallowing (level 5 in Dysphagia Severity Scale). Imaging studies such as cervical CT scan revealed extensive ossification of the anterior longitudinal ligament consistent with DISH involving the cervical spine at the C4/C7 level (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Conservative management, including analgesics and physical therapy, failed to provide relief of symptoms, prompting consideration for surgical intervention.<fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Preoperative cervical CT scan (sagittal and axial images in series) revealed extensive ossification of the anterior longitudinal ligament consistent with diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) involving the cervical spine at the C4/C7 level.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-398-g001" position="float"/></fig>
</p><sec><title>Surgical technique</title><p>The patient was placed in the supine position under general anesthesia. A standard anterior cervical approach was utilized using a right pre-sternocleidomastoid incision, and meticulous dissection was performed to expose from C4 to C7 levels. Intraoperative fluoroscopy confirmed the level of pathology (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The BoneScalpel&#x02122; Ultrasonic Bone Dissector was then employed to precisely perform an anterior osteophytectomy thus removing the excessive bony overgrowth along the anterior longitudinal ligament, with care taken to protect adjacent neurovascular structures and esophagus (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Intraoperative fluoroscopy image in lateral projection confirmed the level of pathology through a needle marker.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-398-g002" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Intraoperative images showing the BoneScalpel&#x02122; Ultrasonic Bone Dissector precisely performing an anterior osteophytectomy, thus removing excessive bony overgrowth along the anterior longitudinal ligament. Care was taken to protect adjacent vascular structures and the esophagus, at the C4-C5 osteophyte (red asterisk) and C6-C7 osteophyte (black asterisk).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-398-g003" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>A diamond shaver, precisely 4.4 mm in diameter with a working length of 34 mm and operating at a frequency of 22.5&#x000a0;kHz, was employed for anterior osteophytectomy. Intraoperative O-arm scanning was performed to document the extent of anterior osteophytosis removal (Fig. <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Intraoperative O-arm 3D reconstructions documenting the extent of anterior osteophytosis removal.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-398-g004" position="float"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec><title>Postoperative course</title><p>The patient tolerated the procedure well without any intraoperative complications. Postoperative imaging confirmed adequate anterior decompression (Fig. <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The patient experienced significant improvement in symptoms postoperatively, with resolution of dysphagia and neck pain. He was discharged home on postoperative day-5 and scheduled for regular follow-up. At the 6-month follow-up, the patient continued to demonstrate excellent clinical outcomes, with sustained resolution of dysphagia and neck pain. Imaging studies at this time confirmed stable surgical results without any evidence of recurrent compression or complications. We have followed the Surgical CAse REport 2023 criteria for the preparation of this case<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup>.<fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Comparison of preoperative lateral X-ray (left) and postoperative X-ray images (right), showing adequate anterior cervical decompression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-398-g005" position="float"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Grauvogel <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> were the first to describe the use of ultrasonic bone dissection for selective bone cutting during anterior cervical discectomy and fusion, particularly for decompression of neuroforamina and removal of posterior osteophytes, highlighting its precision and soft tissue preservation<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>-<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup>. They also demonstrated the effectiveness of angled tips in accessing and cutting bone spurs behind adjacent vertebrae, which are challenging to reach with conventional rotating burs. This feature enhances the versatility of the ultrasonic bone dissector, enabling precise interventions in confined anatomical spaces, such as the posterior longitudinal ligament. These tips can navigate through a 4&#x02013;6 mm disc space to access the spinal canal, making the device suitable for complex surgical scenarios, such as treating ossification of the posterior longitudinal ligament (OPLL) (Fig. <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).<fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Shaver descriptions: the Micro Hook Shaver, measuring 1.3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;1.8 mm, is perfect for minimally invasive procedures and precision work such anterior cervical discectomy and fusion (ACDF), and ossification of the posterior longitudinal ligament (OPLL) treatment (A). The Macro Hook Shaver, sized at 2.2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;3.0 mm, is designed for larger-scale bone shaping and cutting, appropriate for procedures like laminoplasty, transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion/posterior lumbar interbody fusion (TLIF/PLIF), and corpectomy (B). The Diamond Shaver, with a size of 4.4 mm, is ideal for decompression and gross resections, making it suitable for laminectomy, TLIF, PLIF, ACDF, and DISH as in our case (C).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ms9-87-398-g006" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>While existing literature documents the use of ultrasonic bone dissectors in procedures such as corpectomy and the treatment of OPLL<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup>, there remains a lack of studies specifically addressing their application in the management of DISH, particularly in cases involving the cervical spine. This highlights the novelty of our study and its contribution to filling this gap in the literature.</p><p>One of the primary advantages of piezosurgery is its ability to operate without the use of rotating instruments, thereby reducing the risk of damage to surrounding soft tissues. The handpiece is ergonomic and provides excellent operative visualization, although it may present challenges in confined spaces and require adjustments to the direction of the microscope&#x02019;s light. Continuous irrigation helps control excessive heat but may occasionally require additional suction assistance.</p><p>In this case, the removal of anterior osteophytes using the ultrasonic bone dissector took approximately 45&#x000a0;minutes. While this duration may seem prolonged compared to traditional methods, the benefits of reduced soft tissue trauma and precise bone resection can outweigh the time investment by minimizing postoperative complications and promoting faster recovery.</p><p>The ultrasonic bone dissector is specifically engineered for bone tissue resection with exceptional precision (0.5 mm narrow), while preserving underlying soft tissues and minimizing the risk of dural tears or vascular injuries. The console generates an electrical signal transmitted to the piezoelectric transducer in the handpiece, which converts it into mechanical vibrations. A built-in peristaltic pump irrigates the surgical site during operation. The instrument cuts through bone tissue by oscillating its cutting tip at a frequency of 22&#x000a0;500 times per second, effectively preserving soft tissues. Additionally, the device generates heat in the bone, which aids in hemostasis<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>In our case, the mechanical vibration generated by piezosurgery (with an amplitude of 0.05&#x02013;0.36 mm and a frequency of 22.5&#x02013;40&#x000a0;kHz) produces a cutting effect capable of efficiently removing bone tissue while ensuring that the amplitude remains below the elastic limit of adjacent structures, such as the esophagus, thus minimizing unintended damage.</p><p>Surgical management of DISH involving the cervical spine poses unique challenges due to the potential risk of spinal cord compression and the proximity of vital structures<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>-<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup>. In addressing these challenges, the utilization of the ultrasonic bone dissector presents several notable advantages<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup>.</p><sec><title>Advantages and limitations</title><p>The ultrasonic bone dissector offers several advantages, including exceptional precision in bone resection, allowing surgeons to target specific areas with minimal disruption to adjacent tissues. This precision is especially critical in delicate procedures involving the cervical spine, where accuracy is paramount to avoid damage to vital structures such as the spinal cord, nerves, and, in some cases, the esophagus. Additionally, the device minimizes soft tissue trauma compared to traditional surgical techniques, which often involve significant dissection. This reduction in trauma can result in faster postoperative recovery, decreased pain, and improved patient outcomes. The ultrasonic bone dissector also enhances operative visualization, enabling surgeons to navigate complex anatomical structures more effectively &#x02013; an advantage particularly relevant in cervical spine surgeries where precision is essential to avoid complications. Furthermore, its use of ultrasonic energy for bone resection may reduce intraoperative blood loss compared to traditional mechanical methods, contributing to a safer surgical environment and reducing the need for blood transfusions. The controlled and precise nature of the instrument also lowers the risk of unintended damage to adjacent structures such as blood vessels, thus decreasing the likelihood of dural tears or vascular injuries and enhancing overall surgical safety.</p><p>However, there are limitations to the ultrasonic bone dissector. Mastery of the technique involves a learning curve for surgeons accustomed to traditional methods, necessitating adequate training and experience to optimize its use and minimize potential complications. The cost of acquiring and maintaining the system can be substantial, requiring a careful cost-benefit analysis based on the expected improvements in outcomes. Its effectiveness can also be limited in narrow or confined anatomical spaces, where maneuverability is challenging, requiring surgeons to evaluate patient anatomy and surgical requirements carefully. Furthermore, questions of sample size and generalizability must be addressed, as the effectiveness of the ultrasonic bone dissector in diverse patient populations and varying clinical scenarios remains insufficiently studied. Most current evidence arises from small sample sizes or highly specialized cases, which may not fully capture its broader applicability or potential limitations in more generalized settings. These factors highlight the need for larger-scale, multicenter studies to validate the advantages and address the challenges of using this technology in diverse surgical contexts. Despite these limitations, the ultrasonic bone dissector remains a valuable tool in managing DISH involving the cervical spine, offering unique benefits in achieving decompression of neural structures while minimizing soft tissue trauma and preserving surgical outcomes.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The use of the ultrasonic bone dissector facilitated precise anterior cervical osteophytectomy, resolving dysphagia and associated symptoms in this case of cervical spine DISH. Intraoperative O-arm scanning proved valuable in confirming complete osteophyte removal and prevertebral space restoration. This highlights the potential of ultrasonic bone dissection for precise and effective surgical management of cervical DISH. Further studies are needed to assess its long-term outcomes and comparative efficacy, establishing its role in clinical practice.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="equal"><p>Published online 9 January 2025</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent</title><p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient's parents/legal guardian for publication and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal on request.</p></sec><sec><title>Sources of funding</title><p>All the authors declare to have received no financial support or sponsorship for this study.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contribution</title><p>Conceptualization: G.S., M.G., G.P.; methodology, software, data curation, writing &#x02013; original draft preparation: G.S.; visualization: G.F.N., G.E.U.; investigation: G.S., G.P. supervision: G.E.U., B.C.; validation: G.S., M.G., M.F., G.P., G.E.U., G.F.N., B.C.; writing &#x02013; reviewing and editing: G.S., G.E.U.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest disclosure</title><p>All the authors declare to have no conflicts of interest relevant to this study.</p></sec><sec><title>Research registration unique identifying number (UIN)</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Guarantor</title><p>Bipin Chaurasia.</p></sec><sec><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p>Not commissioned, externally peer-reviewed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Data sharing not applicable &#x02013; no new data generated, or the article describes entirely theoretical research.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mader</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verlaan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buskila</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis: clinical features and pathogenic mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Rheumatol</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>741</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24189840</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harlianto</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuperus</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohamed Hoesein</surname><given-names>FAA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis of the cervical spine causing dysphagia and airway obstruction: an updated systematic review</article-title>. <source>Spine J</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1490</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>503</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35283294</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshioka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Demura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Surgical treatment for cervical diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis as a cause of Dysphagia</article-title>. <source>Spine Surg Relat Res</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31440668</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lofrese</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scerrati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balsano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Surgical treatment of diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) involving the cervical spine: technical nuances and outcome of a multicenter experience</article-title>. <source>Global Spine J</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1751</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33590802</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohrabi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maria</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The SCARE 2023 guideline: updating consensus Surgical CAse REport (SCARE) guidelines</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg Lond Engl</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>1136</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umana</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scalia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cicero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Use of bonescalpel ultrasonic bone dissector in anterior clinoidectomy and posterior fossa surgery: technical note</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurochir Suppl</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38153461</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Using piezosurgery in anterior cervical discectomy and fusion to treat complex cervical spondylotic myelopathy is safe and effective</article-title>. <source>Adv Orthop</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>2023</volume>:<fpage>5306445</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38155878</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avrumova</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altorfer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anterior cervical osteotomy of diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis lesions with computer-assisted navigation surgery: a case report</article-title>. <source>Clin Case Rep</source> 2024 Jan 8;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e8427</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ccr3.8427</pub-id>. <comment>PMID: 38197064; PMCID: PMC10774538</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38197064</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Application of piezosurgery in anterior cervical corpectomy and fusion</article-title>. <source>Orthop Surg</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27384737</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grauvogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scheiwe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaminsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of piezosurgery for removal of retrovertebral body osteophytes in anterior cervical discectomy</article-title>. <source>Spine J</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>628</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24314765</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liberale</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bassani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nocini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Step-by-step surgery for diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) of the cervical spine</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>134</volume>:<fpage>2787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37962147</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giammalva</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maugeri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cusimano</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis: a functional enemy of vertebral stability &#x02013; case series and surgical consideration of craniovertebral junction involvement</article-title>. <source>J Craniovertebr Junction Spine</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>274</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37860019</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Surgical treatment of dysphagia secondary to anterior cervical osteophytes due to diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis</article-title>. <source>Medicina (Kaunas)</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>928</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35888647</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renjith</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eamani</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ultrasonic bone scalpel in spine surgery</article-title>. <source>J Orthop</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37216021</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The efficacy and safety of ultrasonic bone scalpel for removing retrovertebral osteophytes in anterior cervical discectomy and fusion: a retrospective study</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>80</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38168463</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>